[SOUND] Stanford University. >> All right well welcome
斯坦福大学
to Stanford CS193P. This is Spring of 2016 version and
欢迎来到 2016 年春季的斯坦福 CS193P 课程
today I'm gonna give you a real quick explanation of what
今天我会快速阐述一下这门课是关于什么的
this class is to make sure you're in the right place. I'm
以免你们来错了地方
gonna talk about prerequisites cuz it's super important to be
也会介绍一下参加这门课程的前提
successful in this class to have the prerequisites.
要想上好这门课，有些准备还是很重要的
Then I'm just gonna give you the briefest overview of what
接着我会介绍一下 iOS 是什么
iOS is. Most of you know because you have iPhones or
你们应该都知道
iPads or something like that, so
因为你们用过 iPhone 或者 iPad
I'm not gonna waste a lot of time talking about that. And
我不会在介绍 iOS 上浪费很多时间
then finally I'm gonna dive right into a big demo that's
最后我会带你们做一个大一点的 demo
gonna build our first application. Cuz I really
直接开始打造我们的第一个应用程序
don't believe in wasting a lot of time with overhead.
因为我不太想花太多时间讲一些理论的知识
We're just gonna dive right in and start learning how to do
我们就直接开始上手做一些东西
this stuff, okay? We only have ten weeks to learn iOS. That's
因为我们的课程只有 10 周
a short amount of time for it. It's a very powerful system.
对于一个这么强大的系统来说，这点学习时间太短了
So we're gonna have to really go at break neck speed. So
所以需要以飞快的速度进行学习
what will you learn in this class?
在这门课程中你将学到什么？
You're gonna learn to build cool apps, all right.
你将会学到如何打造很酷的 App
iOS apps are cool. Why are they cool?
iOS App 很酷，为什么呢？
Well, they're cool because they sit in your pocket, and
因为它们就在你的口袋里
you can bring it out and show your friends.
你可以直接拿出来给你的朋友们看
They're cool because they're really easy to distribute.
还有就是，App 很容易被发布
If you build an app,
如果你开发了一款应用
you can put it on the app store with no work. Boom,
你可以很轻松地把它放到 App Store 上
ship it out to your customers. And also it's a very vibrant,
通过 App Store 把它移交给你的顾客
community. All right? A lot of people doing iOS development,
iOS 开发的社区也很活跃
and they're very excited about it.
很多人在做 iOS 开发，并且他们也很热爱
And, also the apps that you build have animation, a lot of
App 也会包含一些很酷的动画
really cool interactions with users, so they're fun apps to
和用户之间很炫的交互
build. Okay, so you probably know all that,
所以制作 App 是很有趣的
that's why you're here. Another thing you're gonna
你们都知道这一点，这也是你们为什么来到这里的原因
learn though and you're gonna get out of this class
你们还会从这门课中学到
is real-life object-oriented programming.
面向对象编程的知识
iOS is entirely object-oriented in its design.
iOS 在设计上是完全面向对象的
All the writing of code you have to do is object-oriented
你们写的每一行代码都会是面向对象的
programming. And you're really gonna get the experience of
你们将会从现实的面向对象编程中
building a real-world thing using object-oriented
获得很多经验
programming which is a great programming paradigm. And
面向对象编程也是一个很好的编程范式
some of the things your going to learn for example using
你们将会使用
object-oriented programming. Object-oriented databases,
面向对象的数据库
were going to do graphics with object oriented programming.
使用面向对象来编写界面
Obviously going to be some multimedia stuff,
而且还会有一些关于多媒体的东西，
multi threading, animation, networking.
多线程、动画、网络等
All kinds of stuff that you're learning in your other
你们从其它 CS 课程中学到的知识
computer science classes, you're going to do for
都会在这门课程中
real, real life here in this class. So
得到真实的应用
that's really good, it's kind of a good synthesis class or
这很好，这就像一门综合的课程
practical synthesis class for all that stuff.
来运用你学所学到的知识
The prerequisites are really important in this class.
这门课的前提非常重要
The main one is object-oriented programming.
最主要的一个是面向对象编程
I really don't have time in ten weeks to take the time to
我不会在这 10 周中花时间教你们
teach you object-oriented programming first, so
如何使用面向对象编程
you really need to know that coming in. So in terms of
你们需要知道在这门课中会用到
Stanford's prerequisites that means CS106A&B or CS106X.
所以在学这门课之前需要先学习 CS106A&B 或 CS106X
That's absolutely required okay, so you get some
这是必须要有的前提
Java experience in there and a little bit of object-oriented.
所以我假定你们现在有了一些 Java 的编程经验和一些面向对象的基础
And then really important to take some,
在上这门课这之前
just some class where you're gonna do a lot of programming.
上过一些写了很多代码的课程也是很重要的
Okay like CS107 which is not hugely object-oriented but
例如 CS107，虽然没有大量关于面向对象的东西
there's a lot of programming.
但是上那门课会写很多代码
CS108 which is an awesome prerequisite for this class.
如果你在参加这门课之前上过 CS108 是非常好的
Okay, that's basically object-oriented Programming.
它讲是关于面向对象编程的东西
So if you've taken CS108, you're gonna be well prepared
所以如果你上过 CS108，你就已经准备好上这门课了
for this class. CS110, again, not really object oriented
CS110，同样也没有太多关于面向对象的知识
per-se, but there's a lot of coding in there.
但同样是一门非常好的编程课程，因为其中有大量的编程实践
You know, preferably you've taken some other CS classes,
你最好还上过其它的一些 CS 课程
you've written a lot of code because, let me warn you,
写过很多代码
this class is a lot of coding. All your assignments are all
因为上这门课需要写很多代码
coding. You're gonna write a ton of code in this class.
所有的作业都是写代码，你会在这门课中写大量的代码
So if you're not comfortable writing a ton of code,
所以如果你真的不太适应写比较多的代码
then this class is going to be a lot of work for you.
那么这门课程对你来说将是一个挑战
You're gonna find it, maybe you'll be a little underwater.
你会慢慢发现的
Okay so be prepared for a lot of coding.
所以做好要写很多代码的准备
When it comes to object-oriented programming,
当谈到面向对象编程
you should know all these terms like the back of your
你就应该像了解你的手背一样了解这些术语
hand. You shouldn't be looking at those and
你不应该连一些类似
going what, what's that, super class, I don't get it.
「父类」的术语都不懂
Okay, you should not even be here, okay.
如果是那样的话，你不应该来参加这门课程
Go take these other classes and then come back.
先去参加别的课程，然后再回来
This is an upper-level CS course, this is not 106 or
这是一门更高等级的 CS 课程
107. Okay? It's a next level up. So if you haven't
它不是 CS106 或 CS107，它是更高一级的东西
written a fairly sophisticated app before, okay, then you're
如果你还没有写过一些比较复杂的程序
gonna find out whoa, this is a lot of work, okay. So
那你就会发现，你需要学习的东西有很多
that's the prerequisites, make sure you're prepared, for
这就是参加这门课程的条件，确定你已经准备好了
this class. And if you're not, just go take those classes and
如果没有，就先去参加其它课程，然后再回来
come back. All right. So, what's in iOS?
什么是 iOS？
You all know what's in iOS from a user standpoint.
从一个用户的角度，你们应该都知道 iOS 是什么
I'm sure, you've used, all used iOS. So
你确定你们全都用过 iOS
what's kinda under the covers? What are the programming APIs?
但更深层的东西是什么？编程的 API 都是什么？
Everyone know what the words API means? That basically
大家都知道 API 是什么意思
programming interface, it's the functions, and methods,
它其实就是编程接口的意思，它是使 iOS App
and classes that we use to make an iOS app work. So
工作的函数、方法和类
what are those APIs that we use? Well they're huge. Okay,
我们能调用的 API 都有什么？它们有很多
there's so much of it I can barely even summarize it here,
API 实在太多了，我都没办法概括出来
but I'm gonna summarize it by dividing it into four layers
但是我可以把它分成四个层次来总结
okay? The core OS which is kind of near the hardware
Core OS 层很接近硬件
all the way up to Cocoa Touch which is near the user, okay?
Cocoa Touch 层很接近用户
And then there's some layers in between. So
在这两层之间还有一些层
let's talk about these layers,
所以我们先分层次来讨论
let's start down at the bottom there. The hardware.
先从底部开始看，硬件层
So, people don't really realize this, but an iPhone
大部分人都没有发现其实 iPhone 运行着 UNIX 系统
is running Unix, okay? There's basically a version of Unix
UNIX 的最基本版本
running on it, so it has full multitasking, Unix filesystem,
所以它有多线程、UNIX 文件系统
everything in there. And, you know,
所有 UNIX 有的东西
you get the power of that when you build iOS apps, okay? And
在做 iOS 开发的时候你可以运用这些强大的能力
that includes all these things here. Now,
iPhone 包含所有这些
there's some things that this Unix layer, that are specific
还有在 UNIX 这一层特意为了移动设备而打造的东西
to a mobile device like Power Management is really
例如很重要的电量管理
important, Keychain Access to make sure that the people
Keychain，来管理
are not accessing things on the phone that shouldn't,
用户在手机上不应该接触的东西
etc. But this is basically Unix in all its glory,
但这最底层，基本上都是 UNIX 带来的光芒
down at this low level. Next, there's a core services layer.
在它上一层，是 Core Services 层
Because we wanna program in object-oriented programming as
因为我们在编写程序的时候尽量用到面向对象
much as possible, there's a layer which is written in
这一层是在 UNIX 之上使用面向对象语言编写的
object-oriented language, on top of Unix so that you can
你可以在这一层得到
get at things like networking and multithreading and
网络、多线程
network, or preferences and SQL for databases.
或者 SQL 数据库之类的东西
You can get at these things using object oriented APIs.
你可以通过面向对象的 API 来调用这些
So this is kind of an object oriented layer on top of
所以这一层是在 Core Services 之上的面向对象的一层
the core services. Okay but there is no UI in this layer.
在这一层是没有 UI(用户界面) 的
Okay this is kind of base layer. Now the next layer,
有点像比较基础的层
super important. Ironically I don't have a lot of time to
下一个非常重要的层
talk about this in this class. I'll kind of let you know it's
我没有太多时间在课堂上介绍它
there but it'll be something you'll have to dive into
你对这一层的了解取决你想要做些什么东西
depending on what you want to do. But that's multimedia.
这一层就是多媒体层
So this is video, all kinds of different audio frameworks.
在这一层，有视频、音频库
And then of course still pictures like JPEGs,
处理例如 JPEG 图片的
things like that and
图片库
drawing okay the Quartz API for drawing in 2D. OpenGL for
用于 2D 绘图的 Quartz API
drawing in 3D. So there's a lot of stuff here okay we
用于 3D 绘图的 OpenGL
obviously don't have time in ten weeks to teach you OpenGL
显然在 10 周的课程之内我不会教你们 OpenGL
you're gonna have to learn that in a graphics class but
你们需要在图形课程里学习
you'll be able to use it here, okay.
并在那里运用
And then at the top layer, this is where were going to
最顶层，就是我们要花几乎所有的时间在的层
spend most of our time, is Cocoa touch, okay.
就是 Cocoa Touch 层
It is object-oriented API for building user interfaces okay?
它提供了面向对象的 API 来搭建 UI
And these user interfaces are not just buttons and
这些 UI 元素不仅仅包含
sliders on the screen. But things like,
屏幕上的按扭的滑块
what to do when you shake your phone? Or
还有当你摇动手机的时候应该怎么处理
using the orientation of the phone as input for example,
或者把设备的方向当作输入
okay. It also includes animation because in iOS,
它还包含动画
in a lot of the apps there's a lot of animation going on.
因为在 iOS 中，大量的 App 使用动画
It's just part of the way it's being built and
它被搭建的时候这就是其中的一部分了
a lot of the stuff at this level is really high
这一层的许多东西都是非常高层次的
level. Like there are objects that basically let you put
例如，你可以对一个对象进行操作
an entire Safari browser in a rectangle inside your app.
把整个 Safari 浏览器放进你 App 的一块区域中
Okay, this one object you just drag it in,
你可以拖进来一个对象
boom you've got it. All you have to do,
然后你就有对应的功能了
maybe wire up the back button and you're ready to go.
你也许只需要做一个连线就可以了
Same thing with maps. You've seen the whole map 3D maps and
关于地图，你可能见过一些 2D，3D 地图
all that stuff. Again one thing you drag it in,
同样的，你把它拖进来
now you've got full map functionality
你就有了全部地图相关的功能
in you application. So this is super powerful objects. Again
它是非常强大的对象
in 10 weeks and I can only show you the basics of this.
在 10 周的课程内，我只能展示给你这些对象的基本用途
Hopefully the things I've chosen to teach you
好在我选择教给你们的东西
will have paradigms for using them. That you can apply to
都有一些使用的范式
the things that I don't have time to teach you, okay.
你可以把它运用到我没有教给你的东西上面
So I'm going to try and teach you the basics
所以我会尽量教给你们让
of how to make it all work in a way that lets you go out and
这些东西基本运行起来的方式
learn new things quite straightforwardly. Okay, so
然后你们就可以通过这种方式来直接学习新的东西了
that's basically what's an iOS in three minutes or less.
所以这就是关于什么是 iOS 的小演讲
The components of the platform that we're gonna be developing
以下这些东西是在这个平台开发所需要的
on are as follows. First, there's some tools. Really,
首先是工具
Xcode 7 is 99% of what you're gonna be using in this class.
99% 的时间你们都要使用 Xcode 7
Okay? It's your editor, your debugger,
它是编辑器，debug 的工具
source code management, everything is in Xcode7,
源码管理，Xcode 7 都有
it's kind of a one stop shop. There is an extra thing there
它类似于一个一站式的工具
instruments which kind of plugs in with Xcode7 for
Xcode 7 中还有类似于插件一样的 Instruments 工具
doing things like performance, measurement things like that
做一些性能检测之类的事情
but basically we're going to be in Xcode7. Okay, that's
但是基本我们会在 Xcode 7 中干活
where we're gonna be doing all our work. Language, languages,
编程语言
there's actually two languages you can develop for
做 iOS 开发你可以使用两种语言
in iOS. We're gonna teach you the more modern one which is
我们会教你更现代的那个，Swift
called Swift, okay? But there's another one called
另一个叫作 Objective-C
Objective C, I'm not really gonna talk about Objective C
我不会太介绍 Objective-C
in this class, at least not primarily in the lecture. So
至少在 lecture 中不是作为主要讲解的语言
you will have to learn a new language,
所以你得学一门新的语言
I'm sure none of you know Swift, or
我知道你们都不了解 Swift
if you do, it's because you already know iOS.
如果你了解，是因为你对 iOS 也已经有了了解
So Swift will be a new language you'll have to learn,
Swift 会作为你们必须要学习的新语言
I'll spend the first two weeks really trying to
前两周我会尽力用火箭一般的速度
give you rocket speed learning of this new language.
给你们讲解这门新的语言
Then there's a lot of frameworks,
然后还有大量的框架
like foundation and UI kit which is the kinda that base
例如 Foundation 和 UIKit
core services stuff and the UI stuff, but
它们分别是核心服务和 UI 之类的东西
there's also core data and core motion and map kit for
还有 Core Data、 Core Motion 和 MapKit
all these things like the gyro and the accelerometer and
它们分别是对象数据库、陀螺仪和加速计
the object database so there's a lot of frameworks and
还有地图相关的东西
we'll cover as many of them as we can. And
还有一些其它的框架，我们将会尽可能地介绍它们
really just as important of all these things,
还有和这些东西一样重要的一样东西
there's a design strategy or design methodology, okay, for
就是设计 iOS 应用的一种设计策略或设计方式
iOS called MVC, it's used on other platforms as well.
叫作 MVC，在其它平台上也有应用
How many people here have programmed before in an MVC
有多少同学在之前使用过 MVC
type of environment? See, so about half of you.
哦，大概一半
Now I'm going to, since it's only half of you,
既然只有一半的人了解 MVC
I will spend Wednesday,
在周三 lecture
the start of the lecture, explaining MVC. Okay, how,
开始的时候，我会介绍 MVC
what MVC is, how it applies in iOS development. But it's very
什么是 MVC，在 iOS 开发中如何运用
important to know, it's a very important thing to know. And
这都非常重要
I'm even going to mention it a little bit in my demo today.
我也会在今天的 demo 中介绍一些
And I'll just give you the 10 second overview of
我只会给你们简单地讲述一下它
it. Because I can't really do anything, I can't show you any
因为我还不能做任何事情
demo without talking about MVC, it's that important.
在介绍 MVC 之前我不能做任何 demo，它就是这么重要
Okay? So this next slide here is kind of giving you
下一张幻灯片简单地介绍了一下
a summary of what I'm gonna show you in the demo today.
今天的这个 demo 大概要做些什么
You don't need to read this slide now,
你现在还不需要阅读这上面的内容
my slides will be posted for you so you'll always going to
幻灯片都会在课后发给你们
be able to go back. This is a kind of slide you go back and
这一张就是那种课后回去阅读
look at later to make sure, yeah did I understand that in
问问自己到底有没有看懂之类的幻灯片
the demo, etc. Also as I'm doing the demo you'll
你们还会有我做 demo 时候的视频
have the video of it. You'll have a video of this demo so
所以在我做 demo 的时候
you don't need to furiously take notes or
你们不需要非常着急地记笔记
try to follow along to understand what I'm doing.
或者完全跟着我同步做
You can watch it at your leisure later.
你可以在课后看视频
All right, so I'm not going get back to my slides before,
在 demo 之后，就不回放之前的幻灯片了
after the demo so let me tell you what's coming up and then
所以我先告诉你们后续会发生什么
the rest of this is gonna be a demo. Today I have assigned
然后这门课的后半部分都会是 demo
and it's on Piasa already, reading assignment number 1.
今天我已经把第一次作业放到 Piazza（他们的课程平台） 上了
Okay, the reading assignments in this class are all learning
这节课的阅读作业都是关于 Swift 的
Swift. You're gonna have three reading assignments and
一共会有三次阅读作业
all of the three of them are gonna basically
这几次作业
take you through the entire Swift language guide, okay. So
会让你对 Swift 有一个完整的了解
that's what the reading assignments are all about.
阅读作业的内容就是这些
On Wednesday, I'm gonna continue the demo that I'm
周三，我会继续进行这个 demo
doing today. I'm gonna talk about MVC as I said and
会介绍 MVC
then programming assignment number 1 will go out. And
第一次编程作业也会放出
that's going to be due one week later.
一周后截至
Before lecture the next Wednesday. On Friday we
在下周三的 lecture 之前
have an optional section, room and time to be determined.
会有个可选的部分，时间和地点有待确定
Probably around 1 o' clock. I'm not sure where.
也许 1 点左右，我也不太确定在哪
This Friday's and each Friday sometimes we'll have these
有的周五都会有课
sections, sometimes not and it's optional,
它们是可选的
you don't have to show up if you don't want to but
你不必须参加
it's gonna be pretty valuable information.
但是课上会有很有价值的信息
This Friday is how to use the debugger, which as you can
这个周五会介绍如何使用 debugger，还是挺有价值的内容
imagine pretty valuable. Next Monday next week in general
下周一
we will be doing more of the same of getting started here
会介绍如何上手
with Swift and Xcode 7. You're, you're reading
Swift 和 Xcode 7
assignment from today is gonna be due on Monday, and
今天的阅读作业会在周一之前截至
then, you'll have Reading Assignment 2 go
接下来会有第二个阅读作业
out which will be due the next Monday, so
下周一之前截至
the Reading Assignments for the first three weeks
前三周的阅读作业
are overlapping the Program Assignments. The first two
和编程作业是重叠的
programing assign- assignments are quite easy. So
前两个作业是比较简单的
there won't be a problem where you're really overloaded.
所以这些作业对于你们来说也不会显得很多
Starting with programming assignment number 3,
第三次编程作业
it gets quite a bit steeper, okay.
会有一个很大的跳跃
Question? >> The programming
有问题？
assignments, they ask you to solve specific tasks?
>> 编程作业是解决特定的编程任务吗？
Are there any ones that are more predicted?
会有一些主观的问题吗？
>> Yes, so the question is
>> 问题是，
do the programming assignments ask you to solve
编程作业是让你解决特定的编程任务
a specific task, or are they kind of open-ended? And
还是有一些开放性的问题？
the answer is the program assignments have very specific
答案是，编程作业有很明确的需求
required tasks that you must do. You can do them any way
你可以通过任何方式完成
you want, but you must satisfy the required tasks.
但是你必须要满足指定的任务要求
As far as open ended is, your gonna have a final project in
提到开放性任务，你们最终持续三周的项目
three weeks, that's completely open ended.
是完全开放性的
You get to choose entirely what you're gonna do,
你可以自己选择你想要做什么
completely on your own, okay? If you read the document
如果你读 Piazza 上的文档
that's on Piazza, it explains all that, okay? So for
上面就会有相关的解释了
those of you who arrived late, read that doc,
所以对于迟到的这些同学，去读文档
get on Piazza, read it, stay on Piazza, it's all about
上 Piazza，读内容，泡在 Piazza 上
Piazza in this class in terms of communication.
Piazza 就是用来交流的工具
So get on there. Okay, all right,
好的
that's it. I'm going to dive right into this demo right
我们现在开始做 demo
here. We're going to start by launching Xcode.
先启动 Xcode
Xcode is free, you just go to the Mac app store and
它是免费的，可以到 Mac App Store 上下载
download it. And when you launch it, you're going to get
启动它
this splash screen is going to appear right here. Let's hide
会显示一个启动画面
these other things. So here's Xcode. This spash screen has
把其它的隐藏起来，这就是 Xcode
a list of all the projects that you've been working on so
启动界面的这个列表包含你当前进行的项目
right now we have none cuz it's the start of the quarter.
现在还没有，因为课程才刚开始
But you'll have you know each week you're gonna
但你应当知道
have more and more projects piling up in this side. And
随着课程的进行，你会有越来越多的项目
then these three choices are the three ways to kinda
这三个先项是进入 Xcode 的三个选项
get into Xcode. 1, Here, playground,
第一个选项 playground
that's basically, it gives you the ability to write iOS apps,
它给了你写 iOS App 的能力
and play with Xcode without building an app. Okay.
但不需要新建一个 App
So you can call APIs, put things on screen, draw things,
所以你可以调用 API，画一些控件或图形等等
etc. It's kind of a playground for playing around with iOS.
它就像一个学习开发 iOS 应用的小训练场
We really won't be using that much in this app.
我们不会在这个 App 中使用它
But in this class, in my demos, but
但在这门课，或者 demo 中
you can certainly you're welcome to use them,
在你了解 Xcode 的过程中，
as you're playing around with Xcode.
还是欢迎你使用它的
It's kind of a fun environment. Down at
它是个很有趣的编程环境
the bottom here you can check out an existing Xcode,
在最下面，你可以添加已有
project, iOS project, that is in Source Code, management.
源码管理的 Xcode 项目
Okay, now we're going to talk about Source Code management
也许会在周五的课程中讨论源码管理
probably at a Friday section in this quarter but
但是不会在
not right at the beginning of the class.
这门课程刚开始的时候就讲
But Source Code manager is basically a way that you can
源码管理就是你可以通过类似数据库的方式
check your code in and out of like a database okay,
来管理你的源代码
so that you can work with a team, each make changes,
通过这种方式进行团队协作
merge your changes, all that stuff.
每个人对代码产生一些修改，然后合并这些修改之类的
So here is where you would check out your project to work
所以这个就是你获取已有源码管理项目的地方
on. And this middle one is to create a new Xcode project,
中间的这个是新建一个 Xcode 项目
a new Xcode App and that's we're gonna do right now,
现在就进行这一项
okay? We're gonna create from scratch a new app. Most of my
从头开始创建一个新的 App
demos involved creating an application from scratch,
几乎所有的 demo 都是从头开始创建的
okay? Just because I think it's easier for
因为在目前阶段
you to learn if there's no magic behind the scenes where
从零开始写项目
things are appearing out of nowhere. So
对你们来说更容易一些
where gonna start from scratch and go from there each time.
所以我们从头开始新建应用
All right, so I'm gonna click on this.
点这里
You can see it wants to create an app for me so
它会为我新建一个应用
it's gonna ask me some questions.
会问我几个问题
First it wants to know what kind of app I wanna build, and
首先，它问我想要创建哪种类型的应用
we wanna build an iOS application. So make sure you
我们想新建 iOS App
click iOS Application here, not watch app, or AppleTV app,
所以确认你点击了 iOS Application，而不是其它的
or an OS X app, okay? We don't want any of that.
我们不想要其它的
We want iOS application. And inside there we have some
我们想要 iOS 应用
choices of the kind of iOS app we wanna build, like a game or
在这里，它问我们想要建哪种类型的 iOS 应用
this master detail which is usually for browsing
例如是 Game 还是为了浏览数据库的 Master Detail Application
a database. We're almost always gonna choose this one,
我们几乎只会先择这一项
single view application. The view there is kinda referring
Single View Application，这里的 View 代表
to the view in MVC, model view controller.
MVC 中的 V
That design paradigm but this is the ba-, most basic
这个模板会为我们的创建最基本的
template and it gives us the least amount of code to start
MVC 骨架，它会产生最少量的代码
with, which is what we want cuz we're learning so we wanna
这也是我们希望的
write the code. We don't want it to, write any code for us.
我们正在学习，所以希望写代码的是我们，而不是 Xcode
So we're gonna pick single view template there.
所以这里选择 Single View 的模板
Now it wants to know a few things about our app,
现在它需要知道关于 App 的几点信息
what the name of our app is, etc. The app we're going
App 的名字是什么等等
to build today is a calculator and it's gonna look quite
今天要创建的应用是一个计算器
a bit like this calculator, not exactly the same, but
它看起来非常像一个计算器，但又不完全一致
similar to this calculator. This is a basic calculator,
它会像这个，最基本的计算器
it comes with Mac OS and it's gonna look like this,
是 Mac OS 上的原生应用
it's gonna have some keypads, gonna have some operations,
它会有键盘，会有运算符
gonna have a little display in here. Basically a calculator,
在这里还会有个小显示器
so I'm gonna call my app calculator.
所以给我的 App 起名为 calculator
So that's the name of this app. When I look at it on my
它就是 App 的名字，当我在手机上查看它的时候
phone it's gonna say calculator is the name of it.
上面显示的名字就会是 calculator
Okay? This organization name can be anything you want.
这个组织名你可以随意填
It's basically gonna appear in the copyright of your code.
它会显示在你代码的版权信息上
Okay? When you write code,
当你写代码的时候
at the top it's gonna say copyright,
在最上面会显示版权信息
whatever you put here. Put whatever you want.
你可以在这里放什么都行
Your name or whatever. This however,
姓名之类的
wants to uniquely identify you, okay, as a developer. And
这里，需要一个不重复的标识
a good way to do it is this reverse DNS notation here,
一个解决这个问题的很好方式是这个逆向的 DNS 标志
edu.stanford.cs193p and then instead of putting instructor,
edu.stanford.cs193p
put your SU net ID. Cuz no one else has that.
在 instructor 那里填上你的学号就好，因为这不会重复
This would uniquely identify you in the universe.
这会在宇宙中唯一确定你
No one else is going to have that organization identifier.
没人会跟你重复的
And then it builds a unique
随后它会产生一个独一无二的标识
identifier from the app by combining these two things.
通过把这两个结合起来的方式
Okay? You get to choose the language you want to program
在这里选择你想要编程的语言
in here. It actually doesn't matter what you choose
在这里选择什么无关紧要
here, this is just going to be the language that the initial
它只会为你创建
template is going to give you it starts out in.
相关语言的初始模板
You can freely mix Objective C and
在写 iOS 应用的时候
Swift when you're building IOS apps. Okay? Back and
你可以把 Swift 和 Objective-C 混合起来
forth they're, you don't have to pick one and be stuck with
你不需要在选择完一个之后就卡在这了
it. We're going to do all of our programming in this class
在这门课中我们所有的编程都会使用 Swift
in Swift however. Then this is whether we want
这里决定我们是要搭建一个
to build an iPhone only calculator.
专属 iPhone 的
An iPad only calculator. Or a universal calculator that will
还是 iPad 的
work on either iPad or iPhone. Okay? And
或者是它们都可以使用的计算器
we're gonna go universal even though the first two weeks
选择 universal，尽管前两周
we're going to be focusing on iPhone only. In the third week
我们只会专注在 iPhone 上
we'll expand our calculator to work on an iPad as well. Here,
在第三周，我们会让计算器在 iPad 上也正常地跑起来
we're not going to be using databases yet, that will be
目前我们还不需要使用数据库
about week six and we will be talking about testing later in
第六周我们会讨论测试
the quarter. Probably in a Friday section again, but
也许在周五的课程中
we're not doing it now so you can leave these unchecked.
我们现在不会处理这些，所以这些不需要勾选
All right, so now I hit Next, and
点 Next
it says where do you wanna put this project? I'm gonna put
它问你想把项目放在哪里
it in my home directory, in a folder called Developer, and
我把它放到 ~/Developer 中
I highly recommend you do the same, okay.
我也建议你们这样做
Home Directory Developer, so all your apps will start
~/Developer，你们所有的 App 都放到这里
piling up in here. Here's the source control thing I was
关于源码管理
talking about, we're not gonna do this at the beginning, so
我们一开始先不管
we're gonna leave this unchecked. All right. So
所以先不勾选
we hit create, and it creates our first app. Now, it's
点 create，它就创建了我们的第一个 App
actually created these six files, over here on the side.
它实际上创建了这 6 个文件，在这侧边
And over the course of the quarter,
在课程期间
I'll show you what all six of these are about. Today,
我会告诉你们这 6 个文件都是做什么的
we're only gonna focus on two of them.
今天我们只会关注这两个
How many of you have used Xcode before, for any class or
你们有谁用过 Xcode？
anything? Okay, so about a third of you.
好，大概 1/3
So let me explain a little bit about Xcode's UI,
我先介绍一下 Xcode 的 UI
what it looks like. You see this area on the left,
左边这里
this blue area? That's called the Navigator and
蓝色的区域，它是 Navigator(导航器)
it's basically for navigating your project.
它用来导航你的项目
And you can do it in different ways.
通过几种不同的方式
This is the Project Navigator that we see right here, and
现在这个是项目导航
it's basically showing you your files.
它用来显示项目的文件
You can arrange them in folders and stuff, but
你可以通过文件夹来重新组织它们
just basically the files in your app. But you can navigate
但只是导航 App 中的文件
by searching, okay, you can type some search text in here,
但是你可以通过搜索来查找 App 文件中的内容
search for it in your app. You can navigate all your
如果你在 debug 的时候
breakpoints if you're debugging. You can go back and
可以在这里查看所有断点
look at all your old builds to see any errors or
查看之前编译版本的错误或警告
warnings you have, okay, even if you fixed it you go back,
即使你已经修复了它们并返回了
and look at them. So the navigator is kind
Navigator 就像是用来关注
of how you keep track of what's going on in your app.
你的 App 到底发生了什么事情的地方
On the right hand side here we have the utilities area,
在右手边，有 Utilities(工具) 区
which is actually two windows, see it's split top and
有两个窗口，分成上下两部分
bottom here. The top part is essentially an inspector,
上部是 Inspector(监视器)
it's going to let you analyze and change attributes of
你可以通过它看到或改变
whatever's selected in this main window. Right now we
在主窗口选中的东西的属性
don't have anything selected, so it's not showing anything.
现在没有选中任何东西，所以没显示任何东西
And this bottom is essentially like a palette. Okay,
这下面的部分就像一个调色板
you're gonna be an artist building your app, okay, and
在写应用的时候，你就是一个艺术家
you're gonna need things like buttons and web views,
因为你需要类似于 button 或 web view 之类的东西
and things like that, to build your app, and
用来搭建你的应用
you're gonna be finding them all,
你会在这里找到它们
and pulling them all out of here. So it's your palette,
然后可以从这里把它们拖出来，所以这就是你的调色板
your artist palette, as you build things. Okay? You can
你的艺术调色板，用来创造东西
show and hide these two side panels with these buttons,
你可以通过这些按扭显示或者隐藏侧面的面板
up here. I will tend to not do command keys, except for
我尽量不使用快捷键，除了复制粘贴
like copy and paste, so that you can see what's going on.
所以你们就可以知道我到底做了哪些事情
But there are tons of command keys in Xcode, and
但是 Xcode 中有大量的快捷键
if you go To Xcode preferences and look under
在 Xcode 的设置界面
key bindings right here you can see all of them and
你可以发现有大量大量的快捷键
there's tons and tons and tons and you can even change them.
你也可以对它们进行定制
Of course if you don't like them but
如果你不喜欢它们也没关系
it has a lot of commands. All right, so
但是它有大量的快捷键
I'll try to avoid using those command keys. So you can hide
我尽量不使用快捷键
those with these things so you have hidden both sides, right.
可以使用按扭来做这些事情
So you can kind of manage your screen real estate.
你可以管理屏幕的分辨率
Now I have a very low-resolution screen here, so
我电脑的分辨率非常低
I have to manage my real estate quite efficiently.
所以为了高效我需要改变自己的分辨率
If you have a higher resolution screen,
如果你的分辨率很高
then you would obviously not be doing as much hiding and
你就不需要把这些东西给隐藏起来了
showing of these things. So if we look at the navigator,
现在我们看 Navigator
what's selected right now?
当前选中的是什么？
It's the project itself at the very top level, this blue bar.
是最顶层的项目本身
This selecting the project.
它选中了项目
So we're actually seeing the project, the kind
所以在主窗口
of settings of the project, in the main window here.
我们可以看到这个项目的设置
This main window. Here are some of them here, right?
这个主窗口，这里有一些设置
Some of these we set on that first page,
第一页有一些可以设置的
like the bundle identifier and whether it was universal or
例如 Bundle Identifier（包的 ID）
iPad and iPhone, etc. But there's plenty more
是通用的还是只为了 iPhone 或 iPad 而造
settings over here. We'll get to most of those settings as
这里还有许多其它设置信息
the quarter goes by. The only setting that's important for
随着课程的进行，我们会逐渐了解这些设置
you to know now, is this team setting.
现在需要知道的设置信息是这个 team
See here where it says team none? You're gonna wanna be
现在上面显示的是 none
able to write your app, and have it run on a device. Okay.
你想让你写的 App 运行在真实的设备上
It has a simulator, which I'm gonna use today.
我们今天会使用模拟器
But you also wanna be able to run on a device. And
但是你想让它运行在真实的设备上
to do that you need to register an Apple ID.
为了这样，我们需要注册一个 Apple ID
So here I already have mine, this CS193p Instructor, but
我已经注册好了
you're going to go down here to add an account, and
不过你需要在这下面添加一个账号
you're going to give an Apple ID and password. Any Apple ID
填入 Apple ID 和密码
will do, you don't have to join any program or anything,
任意一个 Apple ID 都可以，不需要加入什么开发者计划之类的
just any Apple ID will work here. And
普通的 Apple ID 就可以
you'll put the ID and password in, and
填入 ID 和密码
then you're going to select it here. And
选这里
then it's going to appear here, like this. Okay? Now,
它会在这里出现
when you have a team selected now you can plug a device
当 team 有选择的东西以后，你就可以插上一个设备
in and you're gonna get this warning here, no provisioning
会有一个没有证书的警告
profiles found. And you just click fix issue right there.
点这里的 fix issue
You have to be connected to the network at the time,
这时你需要联网
all right? Fix issue and it'll fix that.
它会修复这个问题
It'll basically get the ID of your device,
它会获取你设备的 ID
register it with you as the developer and off you go.
注册成为开发者，然后就可以了
Okay? So you'll need to do that. You only really need to
你只需要在想把 App 运行在真实设备的时候
do that when it comes to running on a device.
才需要解决这个问题
When we're running in a simulator you're not gonna
当在模拟器上运行的时候
need to do that, but you might as well get this started now.
就不用这么做
Okay? Now what about these other files over here in the
Navigator 中的其它这些文件
navigator that it made these 6 files. Well like I said, were
都有什么作用呢？
not going to talk about all of them. This one for example,
我不会对它们每一个都进行详细讲解
assets.xcassetts. That's all your media assets. So that's
例如 assets.xcassets 是存放媒体文件的地方
images, sounds, icons, things like that. Here for example is
图片，声音和图标之类的东西
the app icon which I haven't set so
例如这里的应用图标
all of these are all blank. So we're not really gonna talk
我还没有设置，所以这些都是空白的
about that today but we'll eventually talk about it.
我今天不会介绍，但总有一天会介绍的
And in fact not only am I not gonna talk about
实际上今天我不但不会介绍这个 xcassets 文件
this xcassets thing right here, but I'm also not gonna
同样我也不会介绍
talk about this app delegate or the launch screen or
AppDelegate 和 LaunchScreen 还有
the info.plist. Okay, so I'm gonna select all those and
info.plist 文件
right-click on them and choose new group from selection and
我选中它们
put them all in a folder. Okay, which I'm gonna call
然后右键为它们新建一个组
supporting files. Because that's what they are really,
起名为 Supporting files
they're kind of files to support my app.
因为它们对我 App 起的就是支持作用
You see they're still there,
你看，它们还在这里
I just kind of got them out of the way so
我只是把它们清理一下
we can focus on these two files
这样我就可以关注这两个文件
which is the most important thing to our demo today. Okay?
它俩是今天 demo 中最重要的部分
Now what are these two files? Now is where I have to talk
这俩文件是干什么的？
about this MVC thing, okay? So MVC stands for
现在我就得讲讲 MVC 了
Model View Controller, okay? Model View Controller is a way
MVC 代表 Model(模型) View(视图) Controller(控制器)
of kind of dividing up all the classes in our object orient
MVC 是一种把我们面向对象 App 中的类分成几种不同组的方式
app into three different groups, the model group,
Model 组
the view group, and the controller group.
View 组和 Controller 组
Okay, what are those three groups? The model group is
这三个组都是什么？Model 组是
what our program does It's UI independent.
关于我们的 App 是做什么的，它与 UI 是独立的
So for a calculator it's going to be all the calculating.
对于计算器来说，它是关于计算的
The things that actually does the calculations, right?
它实际做的事情就是计算，对吧？
That's UI independent, that's going to be our model, okay?
它是 UI 独立的，它就是我们的 Model
The view is the user interface that the user interacts with.
View 就是用户直接接触的 UI 界面
So for the calculator it's the buttons and the display and
对于计算器来说就是按扭还有显示之类的东西
all that stuff. That is the view. Okay, usually that's
这就是 View
made of generic user interface elements like buttons and
通常它是由基本的例如按扭之类的 UI 元素组成
things like that. And then there's the controller,
接着就是 Controller
the controller is the glue between the model and
controller 是 model 与 view 之间的粘合剂
the view. Okay, it's the thing that listens to what's
它会监听UI发生了些什么事情
happening in the UI, makes decisions, updates the model,
做出决定，传达给 model，让 model 更新
something changes in the model,
model 里的一些东西就会发生改变
maybe it changes the UI. Okay, back and forth is really where
可能会改变UI，好的，说来说去
the interface, the logic of our entire app really
我们 app 的整套逻辑生存在 controller 里
lives in our controller, okay? So, this file right here,
okay? 所以，这有一个文件
ViewController.swift, that is our controller, okay?
ViewController.swift，这就是我们的 controller，okay?
Our app only has one MVC, okay? Which is the calculator,
我们的app仅有一个 MVC，okay? 就是这个计算器
MVC and this is it's controller, okay,
MVC和它是这个app的 controller，okay?
the C of MVC. Now, here is your first look at Swift. E,
MVC中的 C，现在，这里是你看到的第一个 swift 程序
we're gonna, I'm gonna explain this little,
我等下将会解释一下这个东西
real briefly. You can see that Xcode has thrown in a couple
非常简单，你可以看到 Xcode 里有一些方法
of methods for me. Everyone knows what a method is.
大家都知道方法是什么
They're so exciting that I'm gonna delete them, okay?
我要删除掉它们，它们显得非常 exciting! okay?
That's because I, I don't wanna distract you with a lot
因为我不想你们被这些代码带走注意力
of random code, so we're gonna keep down just to the minimal
所以我们只保留我们要用的代码
code we're gonna use. We don't,
we will be using those methods later in the course.
我们在后续课程中会用到这些方法
Those are part of what's called the view-controller
这些就是所说的 view-controller 的一部分
lifecycle. But we don't need it for our calculator app. So
但我们的计算器里不需要它
let's look at what we have left here.
所以我们看看留在这里的代码
This import is kind of like an include in other languages or
这个 import 就像其它语言里的 include 一样
import in other languages. But this is not a file,
或是其它语言里的 import，但这不是一个文件
this is a module. And in Swift, you can group a whole
它是一个模块，在 swift 中，你可以把一堆类打包在一起
bunch of classes together. And that's called a module. And
这就可以叫做一个模块
when you import a module all those classes will be visible,
当你导入一个模块，里面所有的类都对你可见
if they're public classes, to whatever is using it. So here,
当然如果它们是 public 类的话，不管谁用都如此
UI kit has all these interface things, buttons, text fields,
所以这个 UIkit 里有所有的的界面，按钮，文本框
all that stuff is in there. And so since we're building
所有的东西都在这个模块里，因为我们要做一个 UI app
a UI app here, a calculator, we're gonna import UIkit, and
一个计算器，我们我们要导入 UIkit
you're almost always gonna import UIkit,
你几乎总是需要导入这个模块
okay? Now in our model, where it's UI independent,
现在在我们的 model 中，UI是独立的
we're gonna probably be importing foundation.
我们也许需要导入 foundation 框架
Foundation is that core services thing, okay?
Foundation 是一个核心框架，okay？
Cuz we might be doing networking and
因为我们可能需要网络编程
databasing in our model, but we're not doing buttons and
或者使用数据库，但我们不需要做一些按钮之类的东西
stuff. So those are the two main things you import, okay.
所以这两个模块你需要导入
Here is the definition, declaration really,
这里是 swift 里对一个类进行定义时看起来的样子
of a class in Swift is what it looks like.
You've got the class keyword. This is the name of the class,
你需要用到 class 关键字，这是这个类的名字
ViewController. Now this is a pretty bad name,
ViewController，一个很差劲的名字
okay, because its very generic, ViewController
因为 ViewController 这个名字不够具体
probably be better called calculator controller, or
我们最好叫它计算器 controller
calculator view controller.
或者计算器 view controller 之类的名字
I'm not gonna show you how to rename that now.
我现在不会教你们怎么重命名
But I will show you next week. But this is the name of our
在下周我会展示给你看，这是我们 controller 类的名字
controller class. This colon UIViewController, means that
这个 UIViewController 意味着
UIViewController is the class our controller inherits from.
我们的类继承于 UIViewController 类
This is object oriented program, we have inheritance.
这是个面向对象程序，需要继承机制
This is the inheritance. Single inheritance in Swift.
这就是一个 swift 里单继承的例子
All controllers, all MVC controllers must inherit from
所有的 controller，所有的 MVC controller 都必须
UIViewController either directly or indirectly from
直接或间接地继承于 UIViewController
UIViewController. Okay, then we have a curly brace here,
Okay，这里我们有了大括号
inside those curly braces goes all of our properties and
所有的属性和方法写在这个括号里
methods. Properties are like instance variables.
比方说一些变量
Everyone knows what an instance variable is,
每个人都该知道什么是实例变量
right? So our property, we call them properties in Swift.
在 swift 中我们称 property 是属性
They're very powerful in Swift, the instance variables.
实例变量在 swift 里面非常有用
They can have behavior associated with them and
它们可以被一些有关联的行为改变
things like that. But all that goes inside these curly
但所有的一切都发生在这对大括号里
braces, okay? So that's your intro to Swift.
好吗？ 所以这就是对 swift 的简短介绍
What about this other file over here? Main.storyboard,
这个 Main.storyboard 文件又是怎么回事？
what's that? That's the V for view of our NVC. That's
它是什么呢？就是 MVC 里面的 V
the graphical representation of our calculator.
它代表着我们的计算器的图形界面
So let's click on that, and see what it looks like.
所以我们点它一下， 看看会发生什么
Right now, it's just a big square. Big empty square here.
现在，它只是一个大方块，大的空方块
And I can zoom in and out, so I'll zoom to 50%,
我可以放大和缩小，那我就缩小50%
see? Here's our UI, now, it's kinda interesting,
看，这就是我们的UI, 有点意思对不对
this UI is square, okay? How many iOS products are square?
这个UI是方形的，okay? 有多少iOS程序是方形的？
Zero, right? None of them are, they're all rectangular, okay?
零个，记住了吗？没有一个是方形的，它们都是长方形的
So they're either landscape or portrait, you know, iPads,
而且他们不是横屏的就是竖屏的，你知道的
whatever. None of them are square.
没有一个是方形的
So how are we building our UI in a square UI? Well we're
所以如何在这个方形UI中建立我们自己的UI?
doing that to remind us that we want to build our UI so
时刻谨记，我们要建立自己的UI
that it stretches and expands and moves things around so
它能够伸缩自如，也得能移动UI里的东西
that it will fit in any shape. Okay,
并且能够适应不同的设备
so we're gonna build one UI, it's gonna work on iPad,
所以我们要做一个可以在各种iPad
iPhone, tall iPhones, short iPhones, high resolution ones,
iPhone，长iPhone，短iPhone，高分辨率设备
low resolution, all of them from this one UI. And this is
低分辨率设备，所有的设备只需要一个UI
square to remind us that if this were vertical rectangle,
这个方形提醒我们 如果这是个垂直长方形
probably our UI would look great in portrait, but
或许它更适合竖屏使用
good in landscape. This way, square, it's constantly
这样，对于横屏使用来讲
maybe not so
或许就不那么合适
reminding us that we have to build this flexible UI.
不要忘了我们要做一个足够灵活的UI
Now today, I'm not gonna do that.
今天我并不打算做这件事
I'm gonna build the UI all up in the upper left corner right
我会在这个左上角上建立我们的UI
here so that it looks good in any, or
或许好看
not looks good, but at least shows up in any shape. But
或许不好看，但至少适用于任何设备
on Wednesday, we'll put in the flexibility to make it,
星期三的时候，我们教你们一些方法
do what it needs to do, okay. So, how do we build this UI?
来给它注入更多的灵活性。所以，我们如何建造这个UI?
We build our entire UI graphically. Okay,
我们用图形拖拽的方式，Okay?
with the mouse. Okay, we do not write code,
用鼠标，我们不需要写任何代码
to say put button here, to put text field there. We just
把按钮放在这里，把文本框放在那里
build it all graphically, and wire it up with our mouse. And
我们只需要用图形的方式来完成，用鼠标做这事
so we're just going to dive right into doing that.
现在我们马上就开始做这个UI
I'm building a calculator. A calculator needs some buttons.
我要做一个计算器，一个计算器需要一些按键
So let's start with a button.
那么我们就从按键开始
I told you that in this utilities window at the bottom
我告诉过你们在 utilities 窗口
there's the palette of things you as an artist, and now we
有一个“调色板”提供给你这个“艺术家”
are UI artists here, are going to build our UI out of. And
现在我们就是UI设计艺术家，将要创造我们的UI
you can see there is whoops. Get that back out of the way.
你可以看见，whoops，把它放到后面去
There we go. Lots and lots of things that we can build our
好了，这里面有很多很多东西我们可以拿来
UI out of here, and we'll talk about actually most of these
构造我们的UI,接下面的几周这些东西
in the ten weeks we have, but we're gonna start about
大多我们都会介绍，但从大概这个四分之一
a quarter of the way down with this one right here button.
的位置这的这个按钮开始
And I'm just gonna pick this up.
我将会点击它
And drag it out, it's my UI. Now when I do that,
把它拖出来，这就是我的UI，当我做这事的时候
notice that these blue lines appear and disappear.
注意下这些出现又消失蓝色的线条
The blue lines help you put something in a theoretical or
这些蓝色线条帮你把东西放在合适的地方
conceptual place. Like this would be putting the button
就像这个给我参考，让我把这个按钮放在
in the conceptual center of my UI. So
我UI框架的中心
if I am portrait it's going to be centered in portrait.
如果我竖屏，它会处于竖屏的中心位置
If I go to landscape it will move over and be in landscape.
如果我横屏，它会移动到横屏的中心位置去
Do you understand what I'm saying? These blue lines allow
你明白我在说什么吗？这些蓝色线条
us to put things in various places and
让我们能把UI元素放在很多地方
this is a big part of how we're going to
对于如何做出一个灵活的UI来说，这些
make this flexible UI. But since I told you I'm not gonna
蓝色线条很关键，不过我已经说了周三再来展示
show you that until Wednesday, we're not gonna do that.
所以今天我不会管它
We're not gonna use the blue lines, okay. But you'll see me
我们不使用这些蓝色线条，okay，等到周三
using the blue lines on Wednesday quite a bit and
我才会告诉你们怎么使用这些线条
you'll want to always use the blue lines.
然后你们就离不开它了
The blue lines are super important to building this
对于做一个足够灵活的UI来讲
flexible adaptable UI.
这些蓝色线条特别重要
All right, so we have our button right here, now we
好了，所有现在我们的按键摆在那了
don't want it to say button on there. Okay, we want it to be
现在我不想要这个空白按键呆在那，我想要
one of the numbers this is gonna be part of our keypad.
它变成我们的一个数字按键
So I'm gonna make this be my five button. And
所以我要把它变成“5”这个按键
to change the text you can just double click on it and
要改变它的文本信息你只需要双击它
change it. So I'm gonna make it 5. You notice it also has
然后改成你要的文本，所以我把它改成“5”，
these little handles around the edge. You can use those to
你可以看见这些边缘上的小框框，你可以用它改变按钮的大小
resize it to whatever you want. So this is computer
这是一门计算机科学课
science class, so we'll make it be 64 by 64, okay? Although
所以我们把它做成64*64大小的，okay?
it really doesn't matter what size I make this, because when
不过我把它做成什么大小真的不重要
it starts being flexible it's gonna start you know,
因为面对不同的环境的时，一个灵活的UI
resizing it to fit depending on what's the environment, but
可以让这些按钮自动变换到合适的尺寸
anyway we'll do that. Now other things I wanna change
不过我还是示范下，现在，这个按钮还有一些需要改变的地方
about this button I don't do directly.
但我不直接做
I need to use this top half of the utilities window here,
我需要用到 utilities 窗口的上半部分
which is the Inspector. Okay, now there's different kinds of
这是一个检测窗口，Okay，现在这有一些
inspectors along the top you'll see here. What you,
不同的种类的检测
what's showing now is the Attributes Inspector.
现在你看到的是属性监测
That, that is the attributes of whatever is selected.
无论我选中了什么属性都会展示在上边
Here is the size inspector. So if I click that, for
这里时一个尺寸监测，所以如果我点击它
example here's my 64 by 64 and I can edit it here as well.
这里就是我的64*64，我们同样也能在这里改变尺寸
I can say 200 by 64, see how this got wide, all right?
我可以改成200*64，看这个怎么变得更宽，all right?
We can go back to 64.
我们也可以改回64
Okay. I'm going to go back to the app.
好了，回到我们的app
And we will talk about these other ones the identity and
我们将会在之后再介绍身份监测，这之类些东西
Spector later. But lets go back here to attributes and
回到我们的属性界面
inspector this is actually object oriented. So
这是面向对象的，所以
here I can set the attributes of a button because that's
所以我能设置这个按钮的属性
what's selected here. And also I can set the attributes of
同样我也能设置这个 controls 属性
a control, which is buttons super class, and
它是按键的父类
then attributes of view, which is controls super class.
再设置 view 里面的属性，它是 controls 的父类
So this goes right up the hierarchy of the inherit
所以它们遵循着继承的体系，一个类继承于另一个
hierarchy, rather, and lets me set various things.
现在让我设置一些东西
For example, I want this five to be bigger, so
比如，我想要这个“5”更大一点
I look here in the buttons attributes and I see font,
所以我看看这个按钮的属性，我看到了“字体”
system font, 15 point. I'm gonna click this and
系统字体，15号，我点击它一下
change this to be 30 point system font. Okay,
把它变成30号的字体，Okay
that looks a lot better. And if I go back and look at this
看起来好多了，如果我再回去看看这个计算器
calculator, see how some of the buttons have a background,
看如何使这个按钮有不同颜色的背景
like grey or orange? I want that too so I'm gonna set
比如绿色或者橘色，所以我设置一下
the background of this to something, so I'm gonna
这个按钮的背景色
go down that turns out to be something that button inherits
所以我往下滑，发现这个按钮的背景
from view, right here background.
继承于 view，就在这里
So I can set it by, you know, using crayons,
所以我可以用不同色的蜡笔来改变它
okay, whatever you can use sliders or I can
okay, 无论你用什么都行
use maybe recently used ones like here's light grey, okay?
我可以用我最近用过的颜色，比如浅灰，okay?
So, I've substituted my nice little background here so,
这样我就更换了我们这个按钮的背景颜色
you know, you can go and edit these things and make them
你们可以编辑这些东西，把按键变成任何你们想要的样子
look however you want, what's interesting about what's going
有趣的地方在这
on here is this...there's no code generation step gonna
这里并没有产生任何代码
happen here. You're actually editing these objects live.
你只是改变了这个按键的样子
Okay. By changing things in the inspector you're sending
通过改变检测窗口里的东西
messages to this button to set the way it is and
你在给按键发送信息，把它设置成你想要的样子
then the Xcode has a way to essentially freeze dry
接着 Xcode 就有办法完成你的请求
all the attributes, and it's object oriented.
改变按钮的属性，这是面向对象
In other words, the objects are participating and
换言之，Xcode 能够把这些操作
freeze drying themselves. And in fact, the whole mechanism
转换成对按键对象的代码的操作，事实上
of this part of Xcode which we call interface builder,
Xcode 的这套机制被我们叫做 ”interface builder”
cuz we're building our user interface, is extensible and
因为我们在为用户做界面，它是可扩展的
you can put your own objects in here, okay.
你也可以在这里加入自己的对象
Your own things they draw, custom drawing or whatever.
UI上所画的一切你都可以自己控制
And we'll show you all about that as the weeks go by.
过几周我就会给你们展示
All right. So, I have one button here, that's good.
好的，现在我有一个按钮在这，非常好
I could even run my app right now.
我甚至已经可以运行这个app了
So how do I run this application? You
那么我如何运行它呢？
go up here to the top, you see where it says iPhone 6s Plus.
看上来，在顶栏这，你能看到这上面写着 “iPhone 6s Plus”
This is actually a list of simulators that you can choose
这实际上是你要选择的模拟器列表
to run your app on, all right? So, you could also run it on
来运行你的app，明白了吗？当然你也可以在一个设备上运行它
a device. If you connected a device and did that team thing
如果你连接了设备然后配好对
I was talking about, you can run it on your device here but
我现在讲的是，你可以在你的设备上运行app
I didn't connect a device so
但我没有连接任何设备
I'm going to run it on an iPhone 6. Okay, so
所以我打算在 iPhone 6 模拟器上运行它
I just pick iPhone 6 and then I just press Play right here,
我只需要选择 iPhone 6 接着按下这个运行键
so we press play it's gonna bring up
好了我们按下运行键，它会产生一个
an iPhone simulator okay and
iPhone模拟器
then the iPhone simulator is gonna run this app.
接着我们的app就会在这个iPhone模拟器上运行
Now this iPhone simulator that you see appearing right here,
现在你看到，这个iPhone模拟器上
it's showing our app. This is more than just our app.
有了我们的app，当然模拟器有的不只是我们的app
This is actually a full simulator of the iPhone.
它可以模拟iPhone的各种行为
And in fact, if I go Hardware, Home, that's
实际上，我点击这个 “Hardware”,，“Home”
just like pressing the Home button. You know the little
它就会像真正按在home键上一样，就像
Home button on your iPhone? Watch this. Press Home, and
按你iPhone上的 home 键，看，点击home
it goes to here. And I got Settings, Photo,
它就回到主界面，这里就是些设置，相册
Calendar, Safari, other apps, etc. Okay, and here's my app.
日历，Safari，各种app。Okay?这里是我的app
This my assistive app, calculator has no app icon.
这就是我的计算机app，目前还没有一个图标
But, there it is. Now, I can go back. Okay? So
但是看这里，我可以点进去，okay？
it's really simulating the device here. Now,
所以它像一个真正的iPhone
what happens if I touch this button? Nothing. Okay?
那么现在我按下这个按钮会怎样呢？什么都不会发生，okay？
That's because we haven't really taught our
因为当这个按钮按下的时候
calculator app what to do when this button is touched. So
我的计算器并不知道该做些什么，我还没有教它
let's go do that. Now how are we gonna do that?
所以我们现在来教它，怎么做呢？
Remember I told you that the V, the view here is kind of
记得我告诉过你们的, MVC 里的 V
generic UI buttons and sliders and that there's a model which
这个按键是一个原生的按键，我们现在还没有
we don't have yet okay? And then there's the controller.
一个 model 来控制它，okay？这是我们的 controller
So the way that touching on buttons causes anything to
按下按按键发生的所有事情都是这个 controller 来完成的
happen is via the controller. So somehow we have to connect
所以我们得把按钮和 controller 连接起来
this button up to our controller. In fact,
what we wanna do is, when we touch this button,
所以，我现在需要做的，就是当我们按下这个按钮时
we wanna invoke a method in our controller object, right?
我们想调用 controller 中的一个方法，好吗？
Sounds nice and object oriented.
听起来非常面向对象
That's what we wanna do. So how do we set that up, okay?
那么我们如何完成这件事呢？
We're gonna set that up by getting the controller and
我们需要把 controller 和 view 放在
the view on screen at the same time. Okay, and
同一个屏幕上，okay？
then we're gonna wire it up graphically with the mouse.
然后我们用鼠标把它们连接起来
So let's get both on there at the same time.
现在我们把它们两个放在屏幕上
The way we do that is with this button right here this
怎么做呢？看见编辑栏右边的
little round circle the assistant editor. This brings
小圈圈了吗？点击它可以
up the controller and the view on screen at the same time
把 controller 和 view 放在同一个屏幕上
again I have low resolution so it's all kinda smashed so
这个界面现在很小，那么现在关闭
let's close our navigator and close our utilities. Okay,
左边和的导航栏和右边的工具栏，okay？
and we can share this space however we want. Okay, so
我们可以随便改变，okay？
we have plenty of room for our code.
现在我们有足够的空间展示代码了
And here's our controller. So, now this is gonna seem wacky,
这是我们的 controller，这可能看起来会有一点怪异
but it's actually really, really cool. Okay.
但实际上这非常，非常，酷，okay？
The way that we hook up that button, to call a method in
我们现在把按钮和 controller 里的方法连接起来
our controller, is by holding down the control key, okay.
只需要按住 control 键
I'm gonna hold down the control key.
好，我现在按住了 control 键
And drag, from the button [LAUGH] into my coat, okay.
然后拖动，从按钮拖动到我的代码里来，okay？
Now I know it really seems weird but it's cool, okay.
我知道现在看起来非常怪异，但是也很酷，okay？
So I can put it wherever I want in my class here. And
我可以随意拖动它到我的代码里面
when I let go, it's gonna say okay, what kind of connection
然后当我松开鼠标，需要设置些东西
do you wanna make between this user interface object and
比如我们UI对象和 controller 之间
your controller? And there's really two choices,
需要什么样的连接？这里有2个选择
one is called an outlet which I'm gonna talk
一个是调用 “outlet”，这个我稍后再讲
about in a moment and the other one is called an action.
另一个叫做 “action”
So an action is when you want something that happens in UI
“action” 就是当UI中发生了一些事件后，
to invoke a method in your controller. Okay?
controller 里的方法将被调用，okay？
Exactly what we want here, that's what an action is. So
这就是我们想要的，这就是 “action” 的作用
here it's asking the name, it wants to know the name
那么这里需要一个名字，它需要知道这个方法的名字
of the method. So here I'm touching a digit button,
因为我需要按下一个按钮
so I'm gonna call this touchDigit. Okay.
所以我这在输入 “touchDigit”，okay？
So this is just the name of the method that,
这就是在我的 controller 里
is gonna be created in my controller.
建立的方法的名字
Notice that my method can have arguments.
注意，我的方法可以有参数
You see down here where it says arguments?
你看下面，这里写着 ”Arguments”
It could have no arguments. Okay. Which is fine, right.
它可以不需要参数, 没有任何问题。
I don't want an argument, that'd be fine.
我不需要参数，这样设置就好了
It can have one argument which is the sender, in other words,
也可以有一个参数，叫做 sender，换言之
the button that is sending me this method, okay.
这个按钮会把我送到这个方法里来，okay？
That's really valuable argument, okay. Especially in
这是个很有价值的参数，okay？
this case because I'm gonna have a whole bunch of buttons.
特别是当我有很多按键的时候
They're each gonna be sending touch digit, and
每一个案件都会发送一个数字
I wanna know which one sent it to me.
我会想知道哪个按键发送给我了信息
So the fact that it's gonna pass itself as an argument to
事实上，按键会把它自己当作参数
this method is great. The only problem is if you see this
传递给方法，有个问题就是
type right here any object. That's going to be the type
你看见这里有一个 “any object”，它的类型就是一个 object
of the object. It's this generic any [LAUGH] object
它可以是右边任意类型的对象
thing right here. We don't want that. Okay?
我们不需要，okay？
So when you're doing your homework don't miss this step.
当你做家庭作业的时候，不要错过这一步
Okay? Change this from any object to UI button.
okay？把它从 “any object” 改成 “UIButton”
Because of course the thing sending us this message is UI
因为发送给我们消息的显然是一个 UIbutton
button. It's unfortunate that this is not the default but
不幸的是它不是默认设置
you must do this. Okay? So, this I wanna click Connect,
所以你必须自己搞定，okay？现在，我来点击 “Connect”
this is just what event is causing this a touch on
这是按下按键后会触发的事件
the button that goes up inside the buttons bounds. Okay?
按键会重新“弹起来”
So I'm gonna hit connect right here and
所以我现在点击一下
it's gonna write the code for a method.
它会写下这个方法的代码
You're gonna see your first Swift method here we go. Okay?
你会在这里看到第一个 swift 方法，okay？
This is your first Swift method. Now this is actually
这是你的第一个 swift 方法
not part of Swift. Okay, it's not part of this method.
这里不是 swift 的一部分，okay？它不是方法的一部分
This is something Xcode puts in here. So that this little
这是 Xcode 放在这里的东西
round circle appears. You see that round circle right there?
所以这里有一个小圈圈，你看了这个小圈圈了吗？
If I mouse over that round circle,
如果我把鼠标放上去
you see how it shows me what thing in my view is hooked up
你可以看见，方法和UI里的东西是怎样连接的
to this method you see? Okay so that's what this is so
看见了吗？ 这就是它的作用
that's really not part of the Swift method. Okay so this is
它不是 swift 方法的一部分
all the Swift method. Okay so what is Swift method syntax?
这才是 swift 里的方法，okay？swift 的方法语法是怎样的呢？
Func, okay, func means this is a function on a class,
先是一个func，func 代表的是这个类里的一个函数
a method is essentially a function on a class, right?
方法本质上就是类里的函数，好吗？
I suppose this could be called Method. Like the breaking bad
这可以被叫做方法。
version of what you'll call meth maybe. But func is good,
和《绝命毒师》里的冰毒发音类似，但是 func 是好的
func is good because you can have global funcs also.
func 还好在你还可以写全局函数
Okay, you can have the same syntax outside of a class,
使用同样的语法，你可以在类的外面写一个函数
description outside of these braces.
定义在这些大括号的外面
And it will be a global function.
这样它就是个全局函数
And we're gonna see some of those.
我们之后会见到一些全局函数
Like square root is a function I'm gonna
就像平方根函数
use when I add square root to my calculator. All right, so
比如，当我在计算器里加上根号的时候
that's the key words just like class is the key word for
“class”，这是创建一个类的的关键字
creating a class. Func is the key word for adding a method.
“func” 是添加一个方法的关键字
Touch digit is the name, obviously of this method.
“touchDight” 是它的名字，显然它是一个方法
Parentheses has the arguments, okay?
括号内可以有参数
We only have one argument called sender of type
我们只有一个叫做 “sender” 的参数
UIButton, so that's what : UIButton means.
类型是 UIButton， 这就是 UIButton 的意思
Any time you're defining a type of something in Swift,
当你在swift定义一个东西的类型的时候
colon and the type after the name of the thing.
使用冒号，后面跟着它需要的类型的名字
Okay, and that's true for arguments to methods,
方法中的参数也是这样
it's also true for local variables, everything.
局部变量，所有东西，都是这样
Colon and the type, okay? Now if we had more arguments,
冒号，然后类型名字，okay？现在如果我们有多个参数
they would just be separated by comma, like otherArgument
它们应该被逗号分隔开，如同这个 otherArgument
might be an Int, okay, so I put an Int there.
它可以是一个Int， okay？所以我写一个 Int 在这
So, this is another argument, second argument here, and
所以这是第二个参数
I can have as many as I want, and they each have to have
我需要多少个参数都可以，每一个都需要一个参数名
a key word, which describes, what they are. If this had
来表示它们是干什么的
a return value, it looks like this. Returns String. Okay, or
如果这个方法有返回值，就这样写，返回一个 String
returns Double. Okay, something like that.
或者返回一个 Double, okay?就像这样
That's how a return looks like, okay. Now I'm gonna
return 就这样写，okay？
take a timeout here from writing our calculator and
现在我要开始写我们的计算器了
just show you what its like to call a method.
教你如何调用一个方法
Okay? This is we're declaring the method. What if I wanted
Okay? 我们在这里声明了一个方法
to call this method on myself? Okay it would be recursive
如果我自己想调用这个方法呢？那么就会出现递归
here because I'm inside touched as your butt.
因为这是自己调用自己
I just wanna show you the syntax for calling okay?
我只是展示一下调用方法的语法
So if I want to send something to myself.
如果我想给我自己发送点信息
I use the key word self, and then to send a message it's
我用关键字 “self”，然后发送信息
just like Java you press dot, okay?
如果JAVA一样，按下“.”，okay？
The thing you want to send it to dot and
你想发送什么，按下一个“.”
then you type the name of the method or of the property if
然后输入你需要调用的方法或属性
you wanna access an instance variable exactly the same.
如果你想调用一个实例变量，也是相同的办法
The name of the property or
对某个对象，你想调用的属性的名字
the method that you wanna access in that object.
或者方法的名字
So here I want to do touchDigit and you're going
在这我想调用 touchDigit
to notice here that Xcode is helping me a lot as I type,
你会发现 Xcode 会帮助我输入
it's giving me lists of things that I can choose that
给我一张列表供我选择
are likely. Here touchDigit, it's putting that on the top
这里，touchDigit，在最顶上
cuz that's the only method that is in my class.
因为这是这个类中的唯一的方法
I inherit a lot of methods from my superclasses but
我从父类中继承了非常多的方法
this is the only one in my class and in fact if I just
但这是这个类中的唯一的方法，事实上
press Tab, it starts filling it out. I'm not even,
如果我按下 Tab，它会自动补全，不需要全部手打
I don't even have to type it okay, cuz it knows that's what
因为 Xcode 知道我们想要什么
I want. Now, it takes two argument. The first argument
现在它有两个参数
you just put it in. So the first argument was a button so
这里的第一个参数是一个 button， 所以
maybe, you know, some button or something like that. Okay,
我输入 someButton 之类的东西，okay
some variable that would have to be a button.
某些变量会是一个 button
I don't have one but that's what it would be.
现在我没有这个变量，不过以后会有的
The second argument here, okay, and
这里的第二个参数
I'm just hitting Tab to go to each argument, is an Int,
我按了 Tab 键来跳到每个参数，它是一个 Int
so let's say I put 5, okay, so this is how I would
那么我放一个5在这里，okay，我就打算这么做了
call this thing. Now what's interesting about this is,
现在，有趣的事
notice that this keyword is actually included,
注意这个关键字也出现了
in other languages this would look like this. All right?
在其它语言中会是这个样子，All right?
You would just have the two arguments, sender and
你只需要两个参数，sender 和 argument
argument, but here in Swift, sorry, in Swift,
但是在 swift 里
we put the explicit, name of the argument here for
需要非常详尽，参数名也需要写出来
readability and clarity except for we don't do it with
这是为了可读，清晰，但我们不写第一个参数的参数名
the first one. Okay? The first one we don't do.
okay？不要写第一个参数的参数名
That's because usually the first one is implicit in
因为 swift 里通常都这样做
the name, okay? But, that's what, now there is a way to
okay？非得写出这个参数名的话
make it so you have to do the first one, for but generally
也是有一个方法的，但是最好别这样做
we don't. In other words we don't type sender this.
换言之不要把 sender 写出来
And in fact, it's wrong to type sender that.
事实上，这样做是错误的
>> Would that be an error?
这样会造成错误吗？
>> It would be an error.
是的，这会造成错误
It would not compile. Okay? So that's the syntax for sending.
它不会编译，okay？这就是发送一个消息的语法了
And you'll have to get used to putting these in for
你们会逐渐习惯这样的写法
all the subsequent arguments besides the first.
除了第一个，其他的参数都要写参数名
Okay. So let's gret rid of all this stuff we added. So
okay，删掉这些我们加上的东西
here's our touchDigit. let's just have touchDigit
这是我们的 touchDigit，现在让它
print something out to the console. Okay?
打印个什么，输出到控制台里，okay？
Great thing to know for debugging, and
这是 debug 的好方法，什么的
stuff like that. You do that with the method print. And
在方法里写上打印语句
I'm just going to say, print touchDigit.
我打印一个 “touchDigit”
So it's gonna print touchDigit after the console.
它会在控制台里打印一个 “touchDigit” 出来
Notice no semicolons on the end of lines or anything like
注意，句尾没有分号或其他东西
that. In Swift the carriage return is the end of line.
swift 里，回车表示这一行的结束
And if you wanna put two statements on the same line
如果你想把两条语句打在一行里
you can use a semicolon in between, but
在语句中间加上分号就行了
generally the carriage return is the end of line, okay? So
但一般情况，我们用回车作为语句结尾，okay？
we print touch digit here. Let's go ahead and run and
所以把 print 语句写在这
see if that works. Changes our simulator.
现在运行一下看它是否能正常工作，改变下我们的模拟器
Now, where is the console?
现在，控制台在哪里？
It's going to appear magically at the bottom here as soon as
当有东西出现在控制台里的时候
something appears on the console. So, here we go.
它会神器地从底部出现，所以，here we go
Ready? 5, there it is. There's the console in here. 5 again,
Ready? 5, 它出来了，这就是控制台，再按一下，5
okay we got two of them. Okay, we press a whole bunch of
okay，我们现在有2个5了
times, and get a whole bunch of them. Go back here, scroll
我们按几次5它就出现几次，回到这里来
around. This bottom area has the console on the right,
滚动一下，底部区域里，右边是控制台
and your debugger output on the left. This is where when
左边是调试器，debug 的时候你会用到
we start to do debugging you'll see it on the left.
它会出现在左边
You can hide one or the other, like we could hide our
也可以隐藏它们，我们可以隐藏调试器
debugger and just see our console here. Okay, so
只留下我们的控制台，okay？
this is cool, this is great. Except for we're gonna
这很酷，非常棒
have a lot of buttons not just this one button, this 5.
但是如果有一堆按键而不是一个呢？这是个5
Okay, so let's go back to our UI. By the way you can hide
现在回到我们的UI，顺便说一下
this thing by either dragging it down or pressing this
你可以通过拖拽来隐藏它们，或者点击这个按钮
button up here. Okay, just like you hide this thing
就像你点击这个隐藏这个
with that you hide with this with that. All right, so we'll
stop. Now I wanna make a whole keypad worth of buttons here.
停止运行，现在我想做出一个完整的键盘
Instead of just having a 5, I want a whole bunch.
不只是一个5，而是所有数字
So I'm gonna do that with copy and paste.
我通过复制粘贴来完成
Copy, paste okay? There we go, paste another one here.
复制，粘贴，okay？好了，再粘贴一个
Okay? Maybe this is our 4, 5 and 6.
okay？这个是我们的4，5，6
I can actually select all three and copy paste. Okay.
我可以选中这三个，再复制和粘贴
1, 2, and 3 and may you paste again.
1，2，3，然后再粘贴一次
Go up here. 7, 8, 9 and we'll copy and
移到上面来，7，8，9，再复制
paste one more to make our 0. Okay?
粘贴出我们的0，okay？
So here's our nice little keypad right here. And,
这就是我们的小键盘了
now we can run. And we'll notice
现在我们运行它
that all of these buttons are sending touch digit. You see?
注意所有的按键都会发送信息给 touchDigit
Okay, so they're all sending touch digit.
他们都会发送信息给 touchDigit
Which is good, that's kind of nice. We can also tell they're
很棒，很不错，我们还能通过这个小圈圈
all sending it with this little circle.
看到它们连接在一起
Watch what happens when I mouse over. You see?
看看我移开鼠标会发生什么？看见了吗？
It's selecting them all to say they're all sending it. Okay.
选中了全部按键，他们都能发送信息
But, we really wanna know which one is sending it. Okay.
但，我们需要知道是那一个按键发送了信息，okay
So we're gonna have to look at this sender argument,
所以我们需要看看这个 sender 参数
to see which button is sending us this touch digit.
看看是哪个按键发给它了信息
Okay. So I'm gonna create a local variable here.
okay，我打算建立一个局部变量
This is how you create a local variable, var. The name,
这就是如何建立一个局部变量，var，然后是变量名
which I'm gonna call digit. And I'm gonna set it equal to,
我打算叫它 digit，我打算把它设置成
whatever I get from asking the sender, what its title is.
给被按下的按键的数字，按键的名字
Okay? Now, how do I do that? Well, we know that we
okay？怎么做呢？ 我们知道
send a message to something by doing the object, right,
得到这个名字肯定和sender这个对象有关，对吗？
sender and a dot, okay? Unfortunately, button has, mm,
sender 然后一个“.”，okay？不幸的是
quite a few methods, okay? I mean probably hundreds, okay?
按键拥有很多方法，okay？可能几百个，okay？
Because it's inheriting things from control and view and
因为它继承于 control，view
stuff like that.
类似的东西
So it's a pretty much, a bummer trying to find out how
所以找到按键名似乎还是很困难
to know what to give this. So we need documentation here.
所以我们在这种时候
We need some help, okay. So the way to do that
就需要文档的帮助，okay？怎么做呢？
is you're gonna hold down the option key, okay.
按下你的键盘上的 option 键，okay？
I already showed you Control is an important key for
我已经告诉你了 control 键很重要
dragging between your view and your thing. Now Option is
特别是对UI拖拽来说，现在 option 键
an important key. And when you hold down Option,
也非常重要，当你按下 option 键
look what happens when you mouse over things.
再移动鼠标，看看会发生什么
They get this dash blue underline going. And what that
下方出现了蓝色虚线，这意味着
means is if you click on them Xcode's gonna tell you
如果你点击了它们，Xcode 会告诉你
as much as it can about that thing. So let's click on
关于它们的一切信息，所以我们在
UIButton and when we do we get this little window that
UIButton 这点击，我们得到了一个小窗口
has a complete description of UIButton in here. And really
它拥有关于 UIButton 完整信息，非常重要的是
importantly down at the bottom it has a reference link.
在最底下，有一个引用链接
See this reference link? And if I click this, this is gonna
看见这个引用链接了吗？如果我点它一下
take me to the documentation for UIButton. So there we go.
它会把我带到 UIButton 的文档里，所以我们点击它
Here it is, UIButton. Here's all the methods and
这就是了，UIButton，这是它所有的方法
properties in UIButton. Here's all the description of it.
所有的属性，所有的关于它的描述
And there is all kinds of text here that describes all
各种各样的文本来告诉你这些方法
the methods and how they work, okay.
是如何工作的，okay？
Now, I need to find something about the title so
现在，我要找出关于 ”title”(标题) 的一些信息
I could search here by just doing Cmd+f to search, and
我可以按下Cmd+f进行搜索
I could search for title but unfortunately the title
我可以搜索一下 “title”，不幸的是
is mentioned a lot, see? So that's no good. So
“title” 在文档里被提及的太多了，很不好
I can go over here to the summary of all the methods and
然后我可以看下 summary 这里，它有所有的方法和属性
properties. We could look here. Getting dimensions,
我们可以看过来，看看它包括些什么
no I don't wanna do that. Configuring edge insets we
不，我不想这样做，我们甚至还不知道什么是
don't even know what that is yet. Getting the current state
“Configuring edge insets”，“获取目前状态”这个听起来
that sounds pretty good, getting the current state.
还不错，获取目前状态
Let's see what we've got, button type okay here's how I
看看这里有什么？按键类型，okay，它在这
can get the button's type that's good.
我现在可以得到按键的类型了，不错
Current title, the current title displayed on the button,
“Current title”，按键上的名称
victory, that's what we want. Okay,
胜利了！这就是我们要的，okay？
now when we find something in the documentation we want,
现在，当我们需要在文档中找东西时
you're gonna see that there is a Swift explanation
你可以看见这里有关于swift解释
of it, and and objective C explanation. So we're always
或者关于 Objective C 的解释
going to be looking at the Swift version in this class.
我们看看这个类的解释的 swift 版本
So what is this thing, okay?
这是个什么？
This is not a method because it would say func right here.
它不是一个方法，因为方法前面有一个 “func”
If this were a method on UIButton you would have func.
如果它是 UIButton 里的方法，你会看到一个 ”func”
Instead it has var, that means it's a property.
但这有一个 “var”，意味着它是一个属性
So a property's like an instance variable, okay?
属性就像一个实例变量，okay？
Now this is an interesting property because it's got this
这是个有趣的属性
little terminology on the end, which means it's read only. So
因为在末尾有个这个东西，意味着它是只读的
we can't set the button's title here with current title.
所以我们不能通过它来设置这个按键的名称
Turns out that's because there's another method up here
但是呢还有一个方法
called setTitle forState for setting the button's title.
叫 “setTitle forState“ 来设置按键的名称
Because when you set the button's title,
因为当你设置一个按键名称的时候
you wanna set the title for what state it's in,
你需要知道这个按键的状态
highlighted, disabled, whatever. But luckily there's
高亮？禁用？无所谓
a current title here that just gets you the current title.
幸运的是这里有一个 “current title” 让你获取当前按键名称
In whatever state the button is currently in.
不管这个按键当前是什么状态的
So, here is, so that's why it says var instead of func.
这就是这为什么是 var 而不是 func
Here's the name of the property, currentTitle.
这里是属性的名字，currentTitle
Here is the type.
这里是它的类型
I promised you that it was always colon and type. Now,
我向你保证类型前总是有一个冒号
the type of this is string? >> [LAUGH]
现在这个类型是 String??
>> Wha? Maybe. Okay? We're
啥？可能是吧，okay
gonna suspend our disbelief here because that question
现在刹住你们的疑问，因为这个问号
mark actually means something. We're gonna kinda hope that
意味着些什么，我们希望这是一个 string
this is a string, but it's not going to be. But that's okay.
但它不是，不过没有关系
So we're gonna try and assume it is. All right? So anyway,
我们就假设它是，好吗？
this is how we look things up in the documentation
无论如何，这就在文档里如何找东西的办法
to see the way it works. Now, there's another way to do it,
现在，也有其他办法来做这事
okay, which is even cooler. I type this dot.
更酷一点，我输入这个”.”
I want the title so I'm just going to start typing title.
我想使用”title”，所以我就继续输入”title”
Okay I don't know there is a method called title,
okay，我不知道这里是否有一个方法，名字是title
in fact there isn't. But as soon as I started typing title
事实上是没有的，但只要我输入完之后
it shows me all the methods that start with title.
它会告诉我所有以 “title” 开头的方法的名字
All the methods that include title in the name. See?
所有名字里包含了title的方法，看见了吗？
And all the methods that have T-I-T-L-E in the order. Okay,
还有所有含有T-I-T-L-E这个字母顺序的方法
and it gives it to you in the order you might expect right?
这会按照你期望的顺序呈现
Title first and then. So this is kinda helping,
含有title这个词的优先，别的在后面，这提供了一种帮助
you can search basically.
你可以这么搜索
And when you do this you would quickly see current title,
当你这么做的时候，你快速浏览到currenttitle
that looks like what I want. And you can double click here,
这看起来像是我想要的。你就在这双击
actually, and it will put in there. Okay? So
这样就会出现在这里。
there's our current title. Now instead of printing touch
这就是我们要的currenttitle。
digit we basically wanna print which one, which digit was,
现在我们想打印具体按到的某个数字，而不是“touchDigit”
touched here. So I'm gonna say touched, we could say percent,
所以这里要换成
s digit. Comma digit.
“touched %s digit”, digit
This is what it would look like in C. For example,
这就看起来像是C语音
is everyone familiar with this print F like format?
所以你们对printf熟悉吗
Okay good, cuz you can't do it in Swift.
很好，但你不能在Swift里这样做
Okay. >> [LAUGH]
>> We don't do that in Swift.
我们在Swift里不这么做
Instead, we do backslash, open parentheses,
我们用反斜杠、括号代替
close parentheses. And then we can put anything we want in
然后里面放任何我们想放的
here. Okay clean digit. And we don't need this out here on
删掉digit，引号外不需要它
the side. Okay, so this will be invaluated converted to
所以这会被转换成string类型
a string. Some things can't be converted to strings but
有的不能被转换，但大多数可以
most things can, so you put that in there. Okay,
所以你可以把它放在里面
if you can't you'll get a warning, okay? All right, so
如果不可以，你会被警告
that's how we do that. So, let's go ahead and
所以我们就这么做了
see what's going on. But now maybe we should start paying
继续看看接下来会发生什么
attention to our warnings.
我想现在应该开始注意一下这个警告了
Okay, when you submit your homework, no warnings please.
当你们交作业的时候，不准有警告
Okay, no warnings. And certainly no errors,
没有警告，当然也不能有错误
those are red things those won't build, no warnings. So
有错误的时候就不能build
what is this warning, let's take a look at this warning.
这个警告是什么呢？我们来看看
You look at a warning by clicking on it.
我们通过点击来看一个警告
So I'm gonna click on it, and it says here,
我点击他，这里是这么写的
variable digit with never mutated, consider changing to
digit这个变量没有被改变过
let constant. Okay, what does that mean?
是不是考虑把他变成let型常量。这是什么意思呢？
That means that instead of var here, it wants us to put let.
这里的意思是，希望我们用let而不是var
And in fact, you should always do that. Anytime you declare
事实上我们应该这么做
a local variable, okay, or even a property that is
任何时候申明一个本地变量，或者一个属性
initialized at the beginning and never changes, in other
在初始化后就一直没被改变，换句话说，
words, it's a constant, use let instead of var.
就是个常量，我们就应该用let而不是var
Now why do you want to do that? Two reasons really, one,
那么我们现在为什么要这么做？两个理由
it helps people reading your code realize this thing's
一、这帮助别人读你的代码的时候意识到
never going to change, I don't have to worry about it,
这个一直不会变，不需要去担心它
it's just like a constant. And two, if that thing were for
这只是个常量。二、如果那个东西，
example, an array, or a dictionary, and you use let,
比如说是一个数组或者字典，你用了let
that means nothing can be put into that dictionary or
这就意味着没有什么可以放进字典或从字典拿出
taken out. Or into the array or taken out okay. So
也可以放进数组或从数组拿出
it's how you can create read only arrays and dictionaries
这就是你如何创建只读的数组或者是字典
okay. So, always use let when you are doing a constant.
所以申明常量的时候一定记得用let
And in fact notice that XCode is saying,
注意Xcode这里说的
hey if you click here I'll fix it for you. Okay,
如果你点这里，我会为你修复这个问题
see how it says fix it replays var with let. Sure. Okay, and
看一下它如何用let代替var修正这个问题
it did it and now the warnings gone. Okay, so
所以它做到了，警告没了
let's run, see if this is working. We're crossing our
来跑一下，看看是不是能行
fingers about that whole string question mark thing.
我们越过我们的手指关于整串问号的事情
All right, so here we go, let's press 5.
好了，来按下5
The heck is going on down there? Okay, touched
这下面就会显示数字
optional 5 digit? Okay so what is this optional business.
touched optional("5") digit？这里的optional是什么
Here you all wanna take a deep breath,
所以这里你们得深呼吸
clear your minds, and pay close attention okay. Because
清空你们的脑袋，集中全部注意力
this is a very important thing in Swift, it's ubiquitous
因为这是Swift里非常非常重要的东西
throughout the entire iOS API okay. Very cool feature, but
这在iOS API里无处不在，一个非常酷的特性
it requires a little bit of getting used to in terms of
但是需要一段时间来熟悉这个语法
its syntax okay? This is the feature of optionals. Okay?
这是一个叫optional的特性
In Swift, there is a type called optional.
在Swift里，有一种类型叫optional
It's a type like int or boolean or anything else,
这是一种类似于int或bool的类型
string, it's dictionary, array,
或者是string、dictionary、array这样的
optional. Optional is just a type. This type can only have
optional只是一个类型，这个类型只有两个值
two values. One value is not set. Okay?
一个值是没有被赋值
That's expressed in Swift with the key word nil, N-I-L.
在Swift里表示它的关键字是nil
Nil only means, this optional is not set.
nil只表示optional没有被赋值
That's all it means in Swift. It doesn't mean zero.
这就是他在Swift里全部的含义，这不代表它为零
It doesn't mean a pointer that doesn't point anywhere, like
这不像别的语言，它不代表一个不指向任何地方的指针
in other languages. Nil means an optional that's not set.
nil代表一个optional没有被赋值
The other state that an optional can be is set,
另一个状态就是一个optional被赋值了
okay? Now, if it's in the set state, it can have
如果它在被赋值状态
an associated value, okay? An associated value,
他就可以有一个关联值
which can be of any other type, okay? Actually it also
一个可以是其他任何类型的关联值
could also be an optional. You can have an optional,
实际上，它还可以是一个optional。你可以有一个optional(optional)
optional, but that associated value is just associated with
但是关联值只和它赋值的状态关联
this set state, okay? In the not set state,
在未赋值状态
there is no associated value cuz it's not set. Okay?
它就没有关联值，因为它没有被赋值
Now what does it look like to declare it optional? Well,
那么把它申明为optional看起来是什么样呢？
let's go back with our option key and take a look at current
让我们回过头看一下我们的option key看一下currentTitle
title. Okay, you remember this from the documentation?
还记得这段文档吗？
It says var currentTitle string? That means this is
这里写到var currentTitle: string?
an optional whose associated value is a string. Okay?
这里的意思是这是个关联值为string的optional
So if someone looks at this property and
所以如果有人看到这个属性
says, what type is that property?
当他问这个是什么类型的时候
And they say, it's a string but it's optional no, no.
他可能会说，这是个string，但是是optional。不！
This is an optional and it's associated values of string,
这是个optional，他的关联值是string
okay? Get used to saying, this type is optional, okay? So
要习惯于说这个类型是optional
this is an optional string, that's what would say.
这是个optional string，这才是正确的
It's an optional string, okay? But primarily,
这是个optional string。主要是个optional
it's an optional. Okay, it's associated value is a string.
关联值是string
So this currentTitle, why is it an optional? Well,
所以这个currentTitle为什么是个optional？
because we might have a button here that has no title set.
这是因为一个按钮的标题可能不会被赋值
Not set. Okay, so the title needs to be an optional,
没有赋值，所以它应该是个optional
so it can represent the case where it's not set. Now,
所以它就可以表示没有被赋值的情况
anything can be an optional. Not just pointers, or objects.
所以任何东西都可以是optional。不只是指针或对象
Ints could be optional. You could have an optional int,
int可以是optional，你可以有一个optional int
okay? But here we are representing the title,
但这里我们代表了一个标题
the button, which is the string and it might be not set
这个按钮的标题是个string，这可能不会被赋值
okay? So we need that to be an optional.
我们需要这个是个optional
So how do I get the string, because I don't want
所以我怎么得到这个string
this digit, which currently is also an optional string?
我不希望这个digit，现在还是个optional string
Isn't it kinda weird here when I said let digit equal,
当这里是let digit ＝ 的时候不是很奇怪吗
nobody said how come you didn't say colon string?
没人觉得你为什么不加上:string呢？
Okay? I didn't say the type. I declared a local variable.
我没有说类型，我申明一个本地变量
It didn't even have a type. How was that possible?
我甚至都没有一个类型，这怎么可能？
In Swift, Swift will infer the type all the time, okay? If
在Swift里，Swift会一直推断类型
it's possible for it to know the type it will infer it.
如果它可以在这里知道他的类型，那么就会推断这个类型
And in fact it's wrong really bad coding style to put that
实际上，这里写上类型是个非常差的编程风格
type in there. It's better to just say let digit equal and
这里最好就这么写
let swift infer it. And here Swift has inferred.
让Swift来推断他的类型。这里Swift也做到了
The digit must be of type string question mark,
这里的digit一定会是个string?类型
that's because this is of type string question mark.
因为后面的也是个string?类型
So of course digit has to be that. You see what's happening
所以digit当然也应该是那个类型。你看到那发生什么了吗？
there? So you're going to see type inference all the time in
Swift里你会时时看到类型推断的结果
Swift, it makes your code much more compact,
这让你代码更加简洁
a lot less repeated stuff, is that a question in the back?
很多更少重复的工作，那边的同学有问题吗？
>> Yeah, is that the same for
这对var是一样的吗？
var too. >> Is the question is
问题是：
that same for var too, absolutely it's the same for
这对var是一样的吗？
var, okay? So, how do I get that string though?
完全一样。所以我怎么获得那个string呢？
If this button title is set, how do I get that
如果这个按钮的标题已经有了，那我如何
associated value thing, okay, out of this optional?
从这个optional里面获取这个关联值？
And the answer is you put an exclamation point in the end,
方法是你在最后放一个感叹号
okay. Now, optional is question mark on the end of
optional在定义的末尾有个问号
a declaration. Exclamation point is unwrap this thing and
感叹号是用来unwarp（解包）这个optional
give me the associative value. So this is very succinct,
然后给我这个关联值。这是很简明的
one character for each side of you using this, okay?
每次可以使用一种符号
Question. >> Can you briefly talk about
问题：
why you want the title to,
why you design the title to be optional instead of like
an empty string? >> Okay, so the question is,
问题是
why does Swift have this optional thing instead of just
为什么Swift不直接用空字符
doing empty string to mean a button without a title?
而是用optional来表示一个没有标题的button？
Or maybe for an int minus 1. I don't know. Or for a point or
或者是一个最小为1的int
0 memory address or something like that. The main reason for
又或者是一个指针、一个不占内存的地址或者类似的什么东西
that is for example, pointers to objects in Swift, you don't
这主要的原因是，Swift里的指针
see the memory address. So you couldn't have it be 0, okay,
你是看不见内存地址的。所以你不能让他为0
that's hidden from you. So there'd be no way to do it.
这对你是隐藏的。所以没法这样做
For an int, if you wanted an optional int, is it minus 1 or
对于int，如果你想要一个optional int
0, max int? What is it, it don't know what it is.
它到底是1？是0？还是别的什么？他不知道应该是多少。
So Swift is trying to be consistent across all things.
所以Swift想涵盖所有情况
Ints, pointers to objects, whatever to make sure that
Ints，指向对象的指针
we can tell which ones are not set. Okay, so
无论是什么，要保证我们能知道他有没有被赋值
that's the thought behind it. It's really great actually,
这就是optional背后的思考，非常棒
once you get used to it it's fantastic. All right, so
一旦你习惯这种做法，真的非常赞
we unwrap it with this exclamation point.
我们用感叹号对它进行unwarp
Now what would happen if that current title value was
如果这里的currentTitle没有被赋值，会发生什么？
not set? And this exclamation point tried to pull out
这个感叹号试着去把值取出来
the associated value? What do you think would happen?
你觉得会发生什么
>> Error.
错误
>> Error, yeah, bad error.
错误，是的大错特错
It would crash my app, okay? So
这会让你的应用崩溃
exclamation point crashes your app if you tried to
如果你试着unwarp一个没有被赋值的optional
unwrap an optional that's in the not set state, okay,
感叹号会让你的应用崩溃
if it's nil. Now some of you conservative folks might be
如果它为空。有些保守的人会说
saying I'm never using exclamation point, that's so
他从来不用感叹号
easy to crash my app. Okay? And the answer to that is yes
因为太容易让应用崩溃。但答案是
it is, but sometimes crashing your app is a good thing.
是的，确实容易让应用崩溃，但有时候这是好事
It helps you find a bug, okay?
这会帮助你找到bug
Because something that you expect to be set by a certain
因为有的时候你希望他被赋予一个确定的值
point isn't, and it crashes your app, and
如果没有，那就让应用崩溃
you find it before it goes out to your customer. And some
你在app发布给你的用户之前就找到这个bug
unexpected thing is happening because something's not set.
因为有些没被赋值，会发生一些预期之外的事情
Now, I'm gonna show you a little later how you can
我稍后会给你们展示
unwrap the optional and get the associated value
如何不让应用崩溃的情况下unwarp optional并获取关联值
without crashing. Basically, test to see if it's set and
总的来说，自测一下它有没有被赋值
do it, okay? So I'm gonna show you that in a little bit.
我过一会会做给你们看
All right, so we've unwrapped this, optional.
我们已经unwarp了这个optional
We're gonna crash if it's not set, that's fine. And so
如果没有被赋值会让应用崩溃，这没问题
now, notice when I do the option click on digit,
注意我按住option然后点这个digit
what's the type? String, not optional string,
什么类型呢？不是optional string
string, that's good because we unwrapped it. So now when we
就是string，这很棒，因为我们unwarp了
run, instead of saying touched optional 6 digit down there,
现在跑一下，就不会说touched optional 6 digit了
it's going to say touch the 6 digit, touch 2, touch 4, 8, 9,
而是说touch the 6 digit或者2、4、8、9
okay? Got it? Okay, now, this is going good, but we
明白了吗？这很棒
don't really want this to be printing out in the console.
但我们不想它在控制台打印出来
We want our calculator to have a display and
我们希望我们的计算器有个显示
we want the digits we typed to go in the display, right. So
我们希望我们按下的digits能显示出来
let's go do that. Let's add a display to our
所以现在来做这个。加一个显示
user interface here. We're gonna put it at the top, okay?
到UI上。我们会把这个放在顶部
I'm talking about this thing right up here where this 0 is.
我指的是这个右上角零的这个
And I wanna it to kinda look similar to that,
我希望看起来很像这个
maybe some different colors but kinda like that.
可能是不同颜色，但是类似吧
So I'm gonna go back to my utilities area over here and
现在回到组建的区域
go to the bottom. And this time,
到最底部，这次
instead of grabbing a button, I'm gonna grab one of these,
不是抓一个button，而是抓一个这个
a label. So a label is Read only text,
一个label，label是一个只读的文字
okay? The user can't touch on it, and then type
用户不能碰这个
with the little keyboard on the iPhone, okay? This is read
然后用键盘输入。
only text which is what we want on my calculator. So
这是一个我们计算器上需要的只读的文字
I'm gonna bring it over here, bring it out, again same way
我会让它到这里，拖出来
as before. I can resize it, I can change what's in there,
跟之前一样，我可以重新定义它的大小
I can change the font over here. Let's make this one
可以改变文字。现在让它字变大
really big, how about 40 point. I can even make it
差不多40pt吧。我还可以让它右对齐
right aligned, you know how in calculators usually
你知道一般计算器都是右对齐
the text is on the right so there's an alignment thing for
这里有个label对齐选项
the label here, so we'll do that. Maybe I want to change
我们可以这么做。
the background color for this one too, how about blue, okay
我也想换一下背景颜色，蓝色就不错
there's blue. I don't really like black on blue, here's
但我不喜欢蓝底黑字
a color of the text, we'll go white on blue. Okay, so
这里是文字颜色，蓝底白字就挺好
I can basically set it however I want, okay, got this UI,
我可以随意设置这些
I could use the blue lines by the way,
也可以用蓝线辅助
to line it up nicely here, but again not so important because
这样就可以很整齐的放置
I'm going to do the flexible UI thing on Wednesday, but
不是特别重要的是，我会在周三教自适应的UI布局
I could do it. All right, so now, how about connecting this
我可以做这些。
to our controller? This is a little different because this
那么如何把这个label跟controller联系起来？
is not a case where the user's gonna touch this thing and
这有点不太一样，因为这不是那种用户点一下
it's gonna invoke a method.
就调用一个方法的情况
It's more the other way around. I wanna talk to it.
这是另外一种情况，我想跟它交互
Okay, I wanna put things in the display.
我想把东西放进去展示
So this is communication coming from the controller to
这是一个从controller到显示的通信
the display instead of from a button to the controller. So
而不是一个按钮到controller的通信
we still connect them up in the same way using control and
我们还是一样用按住control拖拽的方式
drag, okay, to put something into our controller. But
把一些东西放进controller
this time instead of action up here we're going to do outlet.
但这次我们选outlet而不是action
And what outlet means is instead of creating a method,
outlet的意思是新建一个熟悉
create a property. Right? An instance variable,
而不是方法。一个实例变量
just like currentTitle is an instance variable, or
就像currentTitle是一个实例变量
property, we're gonna have a property here.
或者一个属性，这里我们有了一个属性
And this property is going to point to this display for
这个属性会指向显示
us so we can access it any time we want. So
这样我们就可以在任何需要的时候获取他
I'm gonna call this property display, not that, display,
我准备叫这个属性display
okay? Luckily it got the type right here, it didn't say any
碰巧这里有类型，这没说有任何对象
objects. It's good, it knows it was a UI label. And don't
这很好，它知道是个UILabel
worry about this storage, weak or strong, we'll talk about
也不用担心这个storage是strong或是weak
that next week, so you can just ignore that for now.
我们下周再说，所以你现在就可以忽略他
Okay, so I hit connect and it creates,
我点击connect，它就被创建了
instead of creating a method here, it created a property.
这里创建了一个属性而不是一个方法
Now again, this IB outlet is just something that Xcode puts,
再一次，这个IBOutlet只是Xcode放这的。
put this little circle here. So
放了一个小圆圈在这里
we can see what it's connected to, so you can ignore that.
我们可以看到这个链接到了什么，所以你可以忽略那个
I told you to ignore weak and
我说了可以忽略weak和strong
strong, so you can ignore that. And so hopefully
所以可以忽略它
this is familiar to you, it looks like current title, var.
这个看起来很熟悉，有点像currentTitle
This is a property on our controller. Okay,
这是你controller里的一个属性
an instance variable, if you wanna think of it that way.
一个实例变量，如果你想这么认为的话
It's called display. Its type is UI label exclamation point.
这叫display。类型是UILabel ！
Okay, now what the heck is that, exclamation point? Okay,
这里的感叹号又是什么意思呢？
I thought exclamation point was unwrapping optionals,
我认为感叹号是用来unwrapping optional的
why is there an exclamation point here, it makes no sense.
这里为什么有个感叹号？这不科学。
And in fact you can put a question mark here because
事实上你可以在这里放个问号
exclamation point also means optional.
因为感叹号也代表了optional
It means the same kinda optional as question mark.
这跟问号表示的optional是一个意思
And I'm gonna leave this question mark, and
我会先在这放一个问号
I'm gonna keep working on this demo, and
继续完成这个demo
then I'm gonna go back and
然后回过头来
change it to an exclamation point, and
把它改成感叹号
show you what exclamation point means. Okay? But
告诉你们感叹号是什么意思。
exclamation point and question mark both mean optional,
当你定义的时候，
when you're declaring. Okay, so now I have this display.
感叹号和问号都表示optional。所以现在你有了这个display
When numbers get touched here, I want to, basically, append
当数字被按下的时候，我想
these digits onto whatever's already in the display,
不管显示了什么都把digit加到display上
all right? So let's go ahead and do that.
所以现在来做这个
We can get rid of this print to the console.
删掉这个打印到控制台的
We don't need to do that anymore. So I'm gonna create
我们不再需要它
another local variable which is also gonna be a constant,
我需要再新建一个本地变量，当然也是个常量
so it's let. I'm gonna call it textCurrentlyInDisplay, okay?
所以是let。我叫它textCurrentlyInDisplay
So I wanna get the text that's in this display currently. So
我想获得现在display里的字符
I'm going to send a message to display here, right? Display.
我要在这给display发一个消息
And the message, we can look it up in the documentation.
这个信息，我们可以从文档中得知
But the message that I want to send is text. Okay?
但是我想发的消息是文字
That gives me the text in the display. This is a UI label
这会给我display里的文字。这是个UILabel方法
method. But this is giving me an error. Okay, and
但这里却告诉我是个错误
the error that it's giving me here is that I haven't
这个错误说我这里没有unwarp display
unwrapped display. You see that display is an optional
你看display是个optional label
label. You can't send text to the type optional Okay, and
你不能把一个text赋给一个optional
optional doesn't understand the message text.
optional 不理解什么是文字
UILabel does. So, we need to get that associated value
但UILabel知道。所以我们要获得display的label的关联值
of label, of a display, which is the UILabel, and
是一个UILabel
we do that with the exclamation point, here.
我们会在这放一个感叹号
And, again, notice it's offering, here, to fix it. So,
注意这里，提供了修复选项
I'm gonna fix it, and i put the exclamation point in
所以我来修复他，就会放一个感叹号在这
there. Now, this is a UILabel. It's an unwrapped,
现在这里是个UILabel，这一个unwarpped
optional UILabel, right? This is a UILabel,
optional UILabel，对吗？这是一个UILabel
and I'm sending it the message text,
我把那个文字值发给他
actually text is a property, just like currentTitle
实际上text是个属性， 就像currentTitle
is a property on button, text is a property on UILabel. And,
是一个button的属性，text是UILabel的一个属性
in fact, if I option+click on it, you'll see var text is an
如果我按住option点它，你可以看见var text
optional string. Why? Because UILabel might be not set.
是一个optional string。为什么？因为UILabel可能没有被赋值
The text in it might not be set. So it also is an option,
它里面的text可能没有被赋值，所以这也是个optional
just like currentTitle. So I need to unwrap that as well.
就像currentTitle一样，我需要同样需要unwarp
Okay? And so now I have a string,
所以我现在有个string
which is the string that's in there. Now you're probably
就是这里这个
getting tired of these exclamation points and so
现在你可能对这个感叹号感到有点疲惫，我也是
am I, and we're gonna be able to get rid of them.
我们将要去掉它
Some in a second here, so not to worry.
一会就去掉，不用担心
Anyway, I have this text currently in display.
不管怎样，我现在在display里拿到了这个文字
So now I'm just gonna say that the displays, okay, and
所以现在，display
I'm unwrapping it, text = textCurrentlyInDisplay. I'm
unwarp它 text ＝ textCurrentlyInDisplay
just hitting tab here, okay, + the digit that was pressed.
我在这慵懒tab键，＋ digit
Okay, notice that you can use + to concatenate strings.
注意你用加号来串联字符
That's really fun. Okay, some language allow that, some not.
这很有趣，有的语言允许这么做，有的不允许
So it does. Notice also that when I'm setting the value of
Swift可以。同时注意我在给optional赋值的时候
an optional, remember text here is an optional string.
记住这里的text 是个optional string
I can set it to be a string, and that means,
我可以把它赋值为string，这意味着
by definition, set this optional to set and
根据定义，是赋值给optional来设定
use this as its associated value. Right? Now,
把它赋为这个的关联变量
how do you think I would set this optional to not be set?
那么你认为我怎么才能给这个optional 赋一个不赋值的状态？
Anyone know? You would say,
有人知道吗？
set this thing to be nil. This keyword means opp,
把它赋值为nill，这个关键字
optional not set. So that would set this text.
表示optional 没有被赋值。所以会赋这个值
It would blank out this text. It would set it to be not set.
这个栏里为空，这会把它赋为没有被赋值
Okay, so an optional you can, when you're setting it,
所以一个optional，在你给它赋值的时候
you can set it to either nil or to an associated value.
你可以把它赋为nil 或者是 关联值
Okay? Sound good? So let's run.
听起来不错？让我继续
All right, so hopefully when we press these buttons,
所以，理想情况下当我们按下按钮
it's going to append it on to the end, here. So let's try
数字就会被加到末尾
five, it did it. Eight, nine, although I'm not really a fan
5，它做到了，8，9，但是我不喜欢
of a zero at the beginning there. Okay, that zero is not
前面有个0.所以
really how a calculator would work. Okay, when I press that
这不是一个计算器应该有的样子。当我按五的时候
five, I'm essentially typing a new number. It would get rid
实际上我是按了一个新数字。
of the zero. So, we really need a way to keep track of
它应该取代0。所以需要一个方法
whether we're in the middle of typing a number or not. Cuz if
来追踪我们是不是在输入中
we're in the middle of typing a number,
因为如果我们在输入中
we do the apend thing, but
那就得把数字加到尾部
if we're not in the middle of typing a number,
如果不是
then we just replace whatever is in that display, right? So,
那就把之前的数字替换掉，对吗？
I'm going to add a new var, okay, a new instance variable,
我要加一个变量，实例变量
a new property, called,
一个新的属性
userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping. >> [LAUGH]
叫做userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping（笑
>> Okay, now you laugh,
我知道你们为什么笑
you laugh because that seems like a lot of typing, but
你们笑是因为这个变量名字太长了
I will never have to type that again. Okay?
但我不会再做第二遍
Because Xcode is always gonna escape complete things for
因为Xcode 总会帮我自动补全
me. So, long names like that are actually good.
所以长变量名挺好的
Okay, you wanna pick the shortest name that, you know,
你可以选一个短一点的名字
it conveys what you want but you want your names,
这名字要能体现出你想要什么
as you know in computer science naming is everything,
计算机科学里命名就是一切，你懂的
you want your names to be very, very, very good for
你希望你的命名对读你代码的人
the reader to understand what's going on, okay? Now,
非常非常非常的好理解
this userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping is a Bool, okay?
userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping 是个Bool
So, I'm giving you it's type,
我给它一个Bool 类型
Bool. It's not an optional Bool. It's just a Bool. So
这不是个optional Bool，就是个Bool
no question mark here. Okay, it's either true or false.
所以这里没有问候，这里无论true 还是false
I'm either in the middle of typing or I'm not.
我不是在输入中或没输入
Now as soon as I put that in there I got an error.
一旦我把这些放在这，就报错了
See that error up there? What? That's not fair.
看到上面那个报错符合了吗？这不科学啊
I didn't do anything up there. What is that? Let's click it.
我在上面什么都没做啊，那是什么？点一下看看
Class ViewController has no initializers.
Class ViewController has no initializers
Okay, now you're doing your homework and you're like,
这里如果你们正在做作业
what the, there's nothing to do, what I just did.
你会发现，我们什么都没做
I just typed in var here, what does that mean? Okay,
我只是刚才声明了一个变量，这是什么意思？
well the reason you're getting that error is cuz in Swift,
你在这报错的原因是
all properties, every single one, have to have an initial
在Swift里，所以的属性，每一个，都必须有一个初始化的值
value. There's no, you are not allowed to have
如果你不这么做
any properties that don't have an initial value. Okay?
就不能有一个未初始化的变量
So how do we give this thing an initial value?
所以我们怎么给它一个初始值？
Well, there's two ways. One, we create an initializer.
有两种方式，一种，对它进行初始化
That's why you're getting this warning.
这就是为什么会报错
Now I'm not gonna talk about initializers til next week. So
但下周前我不会讲怎么初始化
we can't do that because I'm not gonna talk about it yet,
所以我们不能做，因为我还没讲
okay? What's the other way that we can do it?
所以另一种是什么方式呢？
We can just say = false. Okay, so we just initialize that,
我们直接给它赋一个false 值，我们这就对它初始化了
and the write error goes away. Woo hoo, were winning, and
那个报错就消失了～
I know some of you are saying, yeah,
我知道你们可能会说
what about this one? Okay, you didn't initialize that. Okay,
那么这个呢？你没对它初始化啊
that's because optionals are treated specially.
因为optional 是很特殊的
They are always automatically initialized to not set.
他们会自动被初始化为空
Okay? So this is basically always happening
这就是你申明一个optional 的时候会发生的
when you have an optional, or var that's an optional.
或者是一个var 的optional
Which makes sense, right? You have an optional.
能理解吗？你有一个optional
It's not set until you set it to something.
它没有被赋值，直到你给它赋一个值
So it starts out not set. Okay, so that's why it is set.
所以它会以没有赋值开始。这就是为什么它被赋值了
It's set to not set. Okay? All right, so
它被赋值为没有赋值
we have this thing now, we have this. Let's go ahead and
所以我们现在有了这个，继续
use this thing we created. Actually, I'm going to do one
所有现在用我们刚刚创建的这个
more thing here. You see this : Bool? Do we need that? No.
我还要在这多做一件事。: Bool 我们真的需要这个吗？不
Okay, why don't we need that? Because false can only be
为什么我们不需要这个呢？
a Bool, so Swift can infer that the type of this is Bool.
因为false 只能是个Bool 型。所以Swift 可以推倒它就是个Bool 型
See that? Okay? All right. So, we have this
看到了吗？所以我们现在有了userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping
userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping. We only wanna do this business
我们只想它处理
right here if the user is in the middle of typing.
用户是不是正在输入中的问题
So now we're gonna see in if statement.
所以我接下来输入
If the user is in the middle of typing,
If userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping
now again, I'm just hitting Tab here. Look Mom, no hands,
我按下Tab，这一串就输入好了。
or one hand. If the user is in the middle of typing,
If userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping
then we're gonna do this thing. Okay.
然后我们做这些
If the user's not in the middle of typing,
如果用户不是在输入中
then we're gonna set the displays text
那么就让display 的数字
equal to the digit we just typed. Okay, the five, or
等于digit的数字，5，或者别的什么
whatever, we're gonna replace what's in the display. And,
我们会替换display 里的数字
of course, in either case, the user is definitely, no long,
当然，另一种情况，用户
is definitely, now, in the middle of typing. Okay,
一定是在输入中
cuz you just touched a digit, we're clearly in the middle of
因为你刚刚按了输入按钮，我们显然是在输入中
typing. Now I'm getting pretty tired of typing display
我现在真的对没错都
exclamation point all the time, okay?
输入display! 感到疲惫
All the time typing display exclamation point, when in
每次都输入display! ，实际上
fact, I know that that display is pretty much always set.
我知道display 一定是被赋值的状态
Okay, the only time that this is not set is for
它唯一没被赋值的时间就是
a nanosecond when this starts to come on screen,
当他一出现在屏幕上的时候
before iOS has a chance to wire it up to this UILabel.
在iOS 系统把他变成UILabel 类型之前
But once it's wired up, it's set forever. And
一旦他被连接上，那就永远被赋值了
certainly by the time users are touching on digits,
而且很确定的是，当用户点在数字上时
the UIs completely on screen, and wired up, and so I know
UI 已经在屏幕上创建好、链接好了，
that's never going to be nil. Never, okay, in this code. So
所以我知道它用不会为空
why am I forced to type display, exclamation point,
所以我为什么非要
display, exclamation point, over and over, okay?
重复输入display! 呢？
And the answer is you don't have to because we're
答案是你不需要，
gonna go back and change this question mark to be
我们只要把一开始这个问号
exclamation point. Basically if you put the exclamation
改成感叹号。总的来说，
point where you declare it, it says that anyone can use
在你定义的时候放个感叹号，就表示所有对象都可以用这个
this thing, and it will implicitly unwrap it, okay?
就完全的unwarp 了这个对象
It will automatically unwrap it.
这就会自动unwarp
Now its still unwrapping it, so if that was nil,
现在它还是会unwarp，如果他是nil
it will still crash, okay? But it allows me to get rid of all
它还是会让你的应用崩溃。但是它允许我
of these exclamation points. Okay? Because it's implicit
去掉这里所有的感叹号
that there's an exclamation point on all of them,
因为这里的感叹号完全的unwarp 了所有的对象
because instead of putting a question mark here,
因为我在这放了个感叹号
I put the exclamation point up there.
而不是问号
Everyone got that? >> [INAUDIBLE].
都懂了吗
>> It would crash down here,
可能会在下面这里崩溃
in this code down here. As soon as you access this,
这一块代码，一旦你跑到这
if that were nil, boom, it would be unwrapping it,
如果是个nil，就会unwarp
cuz it's implicitly unwrapped >> And again,
因为它被完全unwarp 了
if I change this back to a question mark,
如果我把它改回问号
now I'm gonna get all kinds of warnings down here.
现在就会出现好多警告、错误
See errors, because I'm not unwrapping it, but
因为我没有unwarp 它
if I put the exclamation point,
如果我在这放一个感叹号
now I'm in implicitly unwrapping it everywhere.
这样我就一次性的把他在所有地方unwarp了
Okay, that's called an implicitly unwrap optional.
这样就可以叫它一个完全unwarp 的optional
Very important,
非常重要
Okay, so now let's go see if that fixed everything?
我们现在看看它是不是修复了所有问题
>> All right, so
所以
now hopefully when we press five,
当我们按下5
it will get rid of the zero. Five. There it is, and
就会去掉0显示5
this is still working. Okay? So that's good. We're
我们做的很好
doing great. Our keyboard is basically fully functional at
这下我们的键盘功能完全了
this point. So now we want to add a,
现在要加一个操作
an operation. Now, because of our technical thing,
因为技术上的原因
we're running out of time, but I have 3 minutes left.
我们快没时间了，但还有三分钟
I'm gonna add the pi button. Okay, pi is a very
我要加一个π 按钮
simple operation. It's just gonna put pi in the display.
π 是个很简单的操作。只是放个π 在display 上
So let's do that. I'm gonna do that by taking the 7 button
来做这个吧。我要选中7这个按钮
and copying and pasting it.
复制粘贴它
That's a really bad idea, as you'll see in a moment. But,
现在看来这很不好
I'm just going to do that and call it pi, okay? Now,
但我就这么做了，叫它π
of course, pi is not a digit button, it's an operation, so
当然，π 不是个数字，是一个操作
I'm going to Ctrl drag down here to create another action,
我要ctrl 拖动另外一个操作
a different action.
一个不同的操作
This action is performOperation because pi
这是个performOperation 因为π 是个操作
is an operation. I'm gonna have all my operation buttons
我会把所有操作的按钮叫做performOperation
called performOperation. And of course I'm not gonna forget
当然我不会忘了
to change that to UI button, okay,
把它换成UIButton
either are you on your homework, right? Okay?
你们做作业的时候也别忘了
And here it is, so there's perform operation right there,
所以performOperation 就在这了
okay. And perform operation, I'm gonna do the exact same
对performOperation 我要做跟
thing that I did at the beginning of touch digit,
之前按digit 一样的事情
which is I'm gonna ask the sender which
要问sender
operation are you? So I'm gonna let mathematicalSymbol =
你是哪个操作
the sender.currentTitle. Now of course
let mathematicalSymbol = sender.currentTitle
I want the string so I could do the exclamation point,
我需要字符，我可以用感叹号
okay? But if this were blank, what if I just wanted to
如果这是空的，如果我只想忽略
ignore that operation press? Okay, instead of crashing.
这个按下的动作呢？而不是让它崩溃
Okay, what if it was legal to have that
如果让它为空是合法的
be blank. Okay? I basically want to unwrap
我只想它被赋值的时候unwarp
only if this is set. So the way you do that is
你做这个的方式
you don't put the exclamation point there. Instead,
就是不要在这放个感叹号
you put if at the beginning. And what's nice about this is
如果你在前面放个if
very little typing but also look how it reads, okay? If I
这很好，也看看这是怎么写的。
can let mathematicalSymbol = sender .currentTitle, then I'm
if let mathematicalSymbol = sender.currentTitle
gonna do something. Okay, so it reads just like English,
然后再做一些什么。读起来像是英文
it's a really nice way to unwrap. So inside this if,
这个unwarp 的很好的方式
this will be a string. It'll be the associated
在这个if 里，这会是个string
value of currenttype, Title. Outside of this if,
这回事currentTitle 的关联值
it's not even defined.
if 之外，它甚至没有被定义
mathematicalSymbol won't even be defined. Okay? Super
mathematicalSymbol 甚至没被定义
simple. So here I can just say if mathematicalSymbol = pi,
超简单，所以我们只要let mathematicalSymbol == π
by the way Alt + P to make pi, okay, then I can set my
按alt ＋ P 就是π ，然后设置display
displays. I don't even need the exclamation point anymore.
我甚至不再需要感叹号
Text = pi, which _pi is pi if we
Text = π，M_PI
Alt click on this. This is a symbol. See? M under bar PI.
按alt 点它。这是个符号。M_PI
It's a double. It's a double vision value of PI. Now,
是个double。这是个double 版的π 值
we have an error here. Why do we have an error?
这里报错了，为什么呢？
Because it says it cannot assign a type double to
因为不能把一个double 赋值给
something that is a string question mark, right?
一个string？
We know the display.text right here is a string question mark
我们知道这是个display.text 是个string？
so we can't do that. So, how do we convert this double to
我们不能这么做，所以我们怎么把这个double
a string? And the answer is we have to create a new string.
转换成一个string？答案是新建一个string
Okay, and now you're gonna see how to create new
这样你会看到我们如何
instances of objects in Swift, and the answer is you just put
在Swift 里新建一个实例。答案是
the name of the class and then parentheses and then inside
打出这个类型名，然后把
the parentheses you can put anything that the class
任何允许你转换的值
will allow you to create one of itself with. Okay, and
放在括号里
you can have multiple of these.
你可以多次创建
These are the initializers referred to earlier. And
这是个早前的初始化方式
string happens to be able to take a double as one of
string 可以把一个double
the things that it knows how to create a new string. So
创建成一个新的string
this creates a new string, okay, from a double. So
所以它从一个double 创建一个新的string
the string class knows how to look at a double, turn it into
string 类知道如何把一个double
a bunch of characters that are a double, okay? So
转换成一个字符串
we'll run this. Okay,
所以再跑一下
so here we go, this is still working and if we press Pi,
这还是好用的，当我们按下π
we get Pi [SOUND], we got a problem, okay?
我们得到π 值，但有个问题
It's not fitting the whole Pi,
没有显示全π
all the digits. We can fix that really easily.
我们可以很简单的修复一下
I'm gonna go back to here. And if we look at the inspector,
我们回到这里，看一下inspector
there's a nice feature in label called autoshrink.
有个非常好的UILabel 特性叫autoshrink
And I'm gonna make it so it autoshrinks but
我会让这个autoshrink
no smaller than 9 point, okay. That's gonna fix that one.
不小于9 点。这就回修复
We have one more problem. Okay, so we have,
我们还有个问题
this is working, pi, what's that?
这个π 又是啥
We got a little pi on the end there and also look at this,
我们在最后有一个π，还有，看这个
that, what a mess. So we got two problems there. For
这很不好。我们现在这里有两个问题了
some reason when we press pi, it puts pi on the end.
因为一些原因，当我们按π，最后有个π 在末尾
Well,why is that? Okay. That's because, let's look at
为什么呢？因为看这个
this little thing. Okay. Pi is sending that, right?
π 会发送这个
How about this one? Pi is sending that too.
这个呢？π 也会发送这个
You see, it's sending touch digit and perform operation.
它同时响应两个方法
That's because I copied and pasted the 7
因为我复制黏贴了7
which sent touch digit and then I added this one. Okay,
所以也发送上面的这个方法
now how do we fix that? You fix that by right-clicking on
那我怎么修复呢？
the button. If you right-click on anything in your UI, you'll
可以右击这个按钮
see all of the connections that it has. Very important to
可以看到所有按钮关联的东西
understand right-click, okay. So you right-click and
理解右击很重要
you can see it only has two connections here.
右击，你可以在这看到两个链接
It's connected to touch digit and to perform operation, so
这链接了两个方法
I'm just gonna get rid of the touch digit by clicking this,
我只是需要去掉touchDigit
gone. Now it only does perform digit,
这样就只想响应下面这个方法了
or perform operation, okay. So we fixed that problem where
所以我们修复了
we're just putting pi on the end, all right.
这个末尾有π 的问题
And the other problem was that when we have the pi and
另一个问题是，当我们有π 的时候
I started typing numbers,
再按数字
it thought I was in the middle of typing a number and
会认为你在输入中
it was adding them on. So that's simple, I'm just gonna
会在末尾加数字，这很简单
say userIsInTheMiddleofTyping number = false.
userIsInTheMiddleofTyping = false
Okay, whenever we perform an operation,
无论我什么时候操作
it's gonna wipe out what's in my display so I'm obviously
就会去掉之前display上的东西
not in the middle of typing a number anymore and we have
因为我很显然不是在输入中
a fully functional calculator with one operation. 45 pi 89,
现在我有了个全功能的计算器按钮
okay? So on Wednesday, we'll pick up
周三，我们会继续
with some more, make a more powerful calculator. Sorry to
做个更强的计算器
run over a little bit because of technical difficulties,
抱歉，因为技术难题拖课了一会
see you then. >> For
下回见
more please visit us at stanford.edu.
更多内容详见：stanford.edu